<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The lyfe of the thre kynges of Coleyne]</title>
            <title>Historia trium regum. English</title>
            <author>Joannes, of Hildesheim, d. 1375.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1496</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19162</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5572</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109805</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845450</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845450</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10351</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19162)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10351)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 61:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[The lyfe of the thre kynges of Coleyne]</title>
                  <title>Historia trium regum. English</title>
                  <author>Joannes, of Hildesheim, d. 1375.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Wynkyn de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Enprynted at Westmester :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1496?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Joannes of Hildesheim.  Liber de gestis et translatione trium regum.</note>
                  <note>Leaf A2r reads: "Prologus. Here begynneth the lyfe of the thre kynges of Coleyn".</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E-F⁶.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; leaf A1 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Magi --  legends --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:10351:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10351:1"/>
            <head>¶ Prologus</head>
            <p>HEre begynnyth the lyfe of the thre kynges of Colein fro that tyme ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ought our lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de god almyghty &amp; cam<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Bedleem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhypped hym and offied to hym. vnto the tyme of theyr deth / As it is drawen out of dyuers bol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es and putte in one / And how they were traulla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e fro place to place / ¶ The matere of thiſe thre kynges fro the begynnynge of the prophecye of Balaam preeſt of Madians &amp; prophete that prophecied &amp; ſayd O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſtella et Iacob et erurger homo de iſrael et ipe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur oim gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> That is to ſay a ſlewe ſhall ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of Iacob and a man ſhall ryſe vp of Iſrael and ſhall be lorde of all folke. as is conteyned in the olde Teſtament / ¶ Of this Balaam is altercaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt partyes betwyx the Iewes &amp; the Cryſten men / for Iewes ſaye in theyr bokes that Balaam was noo prophete but an enchauntour. and thrugh whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che crafte &amp; the deuylles helpe he prophecied / Wherfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re in Iewes wrytynge they calle hym an enchaunto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ur and noo prophete ¶ Agayn the Iewes Cryſten men alledge &amp; ſaye that Balaam was a Paynym and the fyrſte prophete &amp; noo Iewe and he prophecy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed to they in that were noo Iewes / And he prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ryght gloryouſly of the Incarnacyon of our lorde and of the comynge of thyſe thre kynges / for yf his prophecye had ben by the deuylles crafte. the deuyll
<pb facs="tcp:10351:2"/>wold not haue forboden to curſe Iſrael / But god by grete loue ſhewed to Balaam by an angell by grete tokens or that he greued god by his euyll counſell / ¶ Alſo in the Iewes bokes is a grete queſtion of Iob whom god wyth his owne mouthe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendyth / of whom the Iewes toke but lytyll hede or none. for he was a Paynym &amp; none Ebrewe / Ferthermore they ſaye that Iob was before Moyſes lawe. and that ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me he dwellyd in Meſopotania. notwythſtondynge the ſcripture ſayth he was of the londe of Hus in Si<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie. and dwelled in a towne that now is called Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bob. that is fro Damaſke a dayes Iourneye. where his ſepulture is ſeen vnto this day / And beſyde that ſame towne ſaynt Poul was caſte downe in the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de &amp; there recouered agayn by Cryſte Ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / ¶ Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes kepe ryght nought of the prophecies of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam ne of his wordes. but in theyr bokes ſette him at nought. of whiche it were longe to telle / </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10351:2"/>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HAN the chyldern of Iſrael were goon oute of Egypte &amp; had wonne Iheruſalem &amp; all the londe lienge there abowte. and no man was har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy in al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> counfree to ſette agaynſt theym for drede that they hadde of theim / That tyme in Inde was an hylle that was callyd Vaws. and alſo they callyd it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hyll of Vyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory / And on this hyll the warde and the kepyng of theym of Inde was ordeyned &amp; kepte by dyuers aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyes by nyghte and daye for the chyldern of Iſrael and afterwarde for the Romayns / Soo that yf ony peple purpoſed wyth ſtronge honde to entree in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> londe of the kyngdom of Inde. anone aſpyes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hylles abowte by tokens ſhewed and warned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kepers of the hyll of Vaws / As by nyghte they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de grete fyre. and by day grete ſmoke / For that hyll of Vaws paſſyd of heyghte all other hilles of Inde and in al the Eeſt / And ſoo whan ony ſuche tokens were ſeen by nyghte or daye. thenne anone all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere of men of that countree made theim redy for to withſtonde yf ony enmyes came / ¶ Wherfore in the tyme of Balaam that gloryouſly prophecyed of the Incarnacyon of our lorde and of the ſterre and ſay de) Orietur ſtella &amp;c̈ (Thenne al the grete lordes and all the people of Inde and in the Eeſt deſyred gret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to ſe that ſterre / And they promyſed for to geue grete gyftes to the kepers of the hyll of Vaws / And
<pb facs="tcp:10351:3"/>hyred theym wyth grete rewardes and gyftes that at ſuche tyme as they ſholde ſe by nighte or by daye ferre or nere ony lyghte or ſterre in the firmamente other wyſe fourmed than hathe be accuſtumed to be ſeen. that Incontynent they ſholde ſhewe lyght and ſende theym worde / And ſoo longe tyme that comen fame and pronyſtifyeng of the ſterre was gretely de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyred and bore thorugh alle the londes of the Eeſt and alſo the name of the hyll of Vaws / ¶ Moreouer of the ſame hylle roſe vp a grete kynredde in Inde and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eeſt. that is callyd the progenye of Vaws vnto this daye / And there is not a more worſhypful kynredde ne more noble and myghty in all the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and all the kyngdoms in the Eeſt. as it ſhall be ſhewed more plainly afterwarde / And the kynredde came fyrſte of the kynredde of the worſhypfull kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges blode that was callyd Melchior that offryd gol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to Tryſte Iheſu / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <p>IN the yere of our lorde a thouſande two hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred whan the cyte of Akon that is called Acrys ſtode in Ioye and proſperite and was enhaunſed rychely wyth prynces and lordes and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo wyth dyuers orders of men of religyon of all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere of dyuers naco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns &amp; tonges, in ſomoche that the name &amp; the prayſynge of the cyte of Akon or Akers was borne thorugh the worlde? And moreouer alle naco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns and tonges came thither bothe by londe and
<pb facs="tcp:10351:3"/>ſée of al manere of marchandiſe of the worlde / Soo there was noo cytee lyke thereto of nobles ne of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thynes and of myghte / Thenne for the grete name and many folde prayſynges and merueyles that we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re there. the gretteſt of byrthe of the progenye &amp; kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>redde of Vaws came out of Inde in to Akon / And whan they ſawe alle thynges there habunde in more worſhyppe than in Inde and in alle the countrees of the Eeſt / Thenne by cauſe of ſo many playſures they taryed there and buylded a fayr toure &amp; a ſtron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge caſtell in Akon for ony lorde or kynge / And they brought wyth theym out of Inde &amp; of the Eeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny ryche ornamentes &amp; Iewelles / And amonge alle other Iewelles they broughte a coſtle we Dyademe of golde arayed wyth perles &amp; precyous ſtones / And in the hyheſt place of the Dyademe ſtode letters of golde and a ſterre lyke the ſterre that apperyd to the thre kynges whan they ſawe Cryſt with a ſygne of a Croſſe beſide hym / And that Dyademe was Mel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chiors kinge of Nubie &amp; of Arabie that offred golde to Cryſte / For thorugh that Dyademe and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytes of the thre bleſſyd kynges god almyghty hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd &amp; ſauyd both man &amp; beeſt of dyuers ſykneſſes / &amp; what man was take w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fallyngeuyll. whan the dyademe was layed on him anone he was hole / ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mayſter &amp; thorder of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plers gate y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ademe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many precious Iewelles. of whyche crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne they had grete offrynges / But after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ordre
<pb facs="tcp:10351:4"/>of the Templers were dyſtroyed where that Dyade me and many other ryght precyous ornamentes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came. it was neuer knowen vnto this daye / Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore grece ſorowe and lamentacyon was thenne ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de in all that countree abowte / ¶ Moreouer the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde prynces of Vaws broughte alſo wyth theym out of Inde bokes whyche were wreten in Ebrewe and Caldee langage berynge wytneſſe of the lyfe &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dedes of thoſe thre reno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med kynges / The why the bokes were after tranſlated in to Frenſſhe / And ſoo of thoſe bokes and of herynge and of ſyght and of ſermon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and of Omelies that ben drawen out of dyuerſe bokes. this preſente treatyſe is thus wryten togyder and compryſed in one libell or lytyll boke / ¶ Alſo the olde <abbr>kynred</abbr> of this Progenie of Vaws beren alwaye in theyr baners vnto this daye a ſterre wyth a ſygne of a Croſſe on the ſame manere and in lyke fourme as it appered to the thre kynges in ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of the byrthe of oure Sauyoure Cryſte Iheſu / ¶ And ſoo alwaye after that the prophete Balaam had prophecied of that ſterre. the more the fame and deſyrynge of the ſterre encreaſed. and the more gret<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly it was had in remembraunce thorugh out all the londe of Inde and of Caldee. and alſo the more the people deſyred to ſe it in theyr lyue dayes / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <p>WHan Ezecheas regned and was kynge and ſouereyne of the londe of Iewes / Thenne
<pb facs="tcp:10351:4"/>Yſaye the prophete prophecyed gloryouſly of our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſaynt Mary and of her ſone. and ſayd) Ecce vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go concipiet &amp; pariet filium &amp;c̈ (Loo ſayd the prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce a mayde ſhall conceyue and bere a chylde / ¶ In the tyme of Yſaye kynge Ezecheas was greued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an Infirmite vnto the dethe / And Yſaye the prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te in the name of god tolde hym that he ſholde deye wherfore Ezecheas torned to the walle and wept &amp; ſorowed. as holy wrytte telleth / And not for drede of dethe oonly. but for he had noo eyre. and for the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſte of Abraham and of Dauid and alſo the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecye of Balaam and of Yſaye ſholde faylle and peryſſhe in hym / Wherfore our lorde had mercy on hym. And encreaced and prolonged his lyfe: xv-ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res lenger / And Ezecheas aſkyd a token of god the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reof / The whyche token was this / That the ſonne ſholde goo bakwarde or wythdrawe hym ayenſt his kinde / And ſoo god ſuffred it to be / ¶ And whan the Caldees ſawe this merueyllous and wonderfull to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the ſonne &amp; in the ayre. they merueyled ryght gretly therof / And whan they vnderſtode that this token was ſhewed for Ezecheas the kynge. thenne they ſente hym many gyftes. and were in purpoſe &amp; wyll to come and worſhyppe hym / For the kynge Ezecheas of very Innocencie of herte made diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lacyon &amp; wolde knowlege that this token was ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed for hym / And alſo he wolde not thanke god therof but had a lytyll pryde in his herte / Wherfore
<pb facs="tcp:10351:5"/>god was ſomdele wrothe wyth hym / And therfore god ſent to Ezecheas by his prophete Yſaye. that al thoſe gyftis whyche were ſente to hym by the Calde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es ſholde be borne in to Babilonie. as is wryten in the Byble / For though Ezecheas were kynge of the Iewes borne. and that wonderfull token was ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed for hym. yet he was not that man that ſholde aryſe vp of Iheruſalem and be lorde of all folke as Ballaam prophecyed / ¶ And in that tyme the Cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dees and the Grekes gaue theim moche to Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mye and had grete delyte therin / In ſoo moche that euery mayde and chylde in mennes howſes knewen the courſe of the ſterres and of the planetes And yet alway they gyue them therto.&amp; ſpecyally kynges &amp; prynces / For they haue mayſters of that ſcyence and gyue theym grete wages to teche theim / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <p>AFter Ezecheas regned Manaſſes. and ſlewe Yſaye the prophete / And after Manaſſes regned Amon. and after him Ioſias / And in his tyme prophecyed Iheremy. and thenne Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>achim / The ſame tyme the Caldees byfeged Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem and dyſtroyed if. and bare away all the veſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell and the ornamentes that were in the temple of god and in the kynges houſe. and bare theym in to Babilonie. as Yſaye hadde prophecyed before / And they ledde many Iewes pryſoners in to Babilonie the whiche is fro Iheruſalem. l. dayes Iourney / And
<pb facs="tcp:10351:5"/>they were in captiuite and in pryſon. l. yere. to whom Iheremye ſent many bokes of the lawe &amp; of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyes. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſholde not be forgete. as the boke tellyth / ¶ And in this captiuyte of Iewes Danyel prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyed vnder Tyrus kynge of Perſe of the Incarnacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of Iheſu Cryſte. and ſayd) De lapide abſciſo de monte ſine manibus conſcidenciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (As ye maye here after / ¶ Amonge all other Danyel ſayd to the Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es) Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> venerit ſanctus <abbr>ſcto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>rum</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </abbr> ſeſſabit vnctio veſtra(: That is to ſay. whan he that is mooſt holy of ſayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes comyth. thenne ſhall your vncco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n ſeſſe / ¶ After this the kynge of Perſe &amp; the Caldees co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded and dyde wryte and tranſlate out of Ebrewe in to Caldee all the bokes of the Iewes lawes and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies of Yſaye. chore Ieremye Danyel Mychie.&amp; Balaam &amp; other prophecies / Among all thiſe bokes &amp; prophecies they fonde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> many thinges ſhold be ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fylled by the Caldees &amp; theym of Perſe. &amp; ſpecyally by the Caldees &amp; theym of Perſe. &amp; ſpecyally after the prophecie of Balaam. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſayd) Oriet<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtella ex Iacob (And for thyſe prohecyes and bokes of the Iewes and for other cauſes the Caldees &amp; the men of Perſe were the more feruente and ſtudyenge after the ſterre / ¶ Wherby we ſhall vnderſtonde that alle this is by goddys ordynaunce &amp; of his habundannte mercy. and alſo to the ſtrenthynge of oure faythe / ¶ Balaam that was the fyrſte prophete and was noo Iewe prophecyed by a ſterre the fyrſte callynge &amp; clepynge of theym that were noo Iewes. whanne
<pb facs="tcp:10351:6"/>he ſayd) Orietur ſtella ex Iacob &amp; exurget homo &amp;c̈ (And this callynge of the people god fyrſte began &amp; perfourmyd by his byrthe &amp; by thyſe gloryous kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / And how be it that thei of Perſe and of Caldee were Paynemes. yet by thyſe prophecyes and bokes of the Iewes they founde and wyſt well that what ſoo euer god had promyſed by his prophetes he was myghty to fulfyll and perfourme it / ¶ Soo they or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned twelue of the gretteſt clerkes of Aſtronomye that were in all the countreee. and gaaf theym grete rewardes to kepe the hyll of Vaws aforſayde. for bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſterre that was prophecied by Balaam ¶ And the cauſe that there were twelue men ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. was this / That yf ſoo were that one man deyed a nother ſholde be put in his ſtede / And nother cauſe was that ſome of theim ſholde kepe the hyll one ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me / And ſome a nother tyme to loke after the ſterre that Balaam prophecyed / Neuertheles the people lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked not oonly after the ſterre but after the man that it betokenyd. whyche ſholde be lorde of all folke / ¶ And they of Inde and Caldee came often tymes to Iheruſalem by cauſe of marchaundyſes and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for playſure / And they for the mooſt parte be ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in Aſtronomye / For in Inde and in other places abowte ben many ſterres in the fyrmament whyche maye not be ſeen and perceyued by nyghte playnly / ¶ But on the hyll of Vaws in a bryght weder and clere ben ſeen &amp; perceyued many dyuerſe &amp; ſtraunge
<pb facs="tcp:10351:6"/>ſterres / This hyll of Vaws paſſyth of heyghte alle the hylles of the eeſte / And aboue it is nomore of bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de than a lytyll chapell that is made therupon / The whyche the thre kynges dyde make of ſtone &amp; tym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre / And there ben aboute this hyll many ſteppes for to goo vp to the chapell / And there growe trees and good herbes and dyuers ſpyces abowte this hyll / for elles men myghte not goo vp to the hyll it is ſo hye &amp; narowe / There is alſo a piller of ſtone aboue that chapell of a wonder height / On the heed of this pyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler ſtondyth a ſterre gylte &amp; well made &amp; fayre. and tornyth wyth the wynde as a fane / And thrugh the lyghte of the ſonne by daye &amp; of the mone by nyght the ſame ſterre geuyth lyghte a grete waye in to the countree abowte / And many other merueylles ben tolde of this hyll of Vaws / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <p>WHan the tyme of mercy &amp; grace was come that god wolde haue mercy on mankynde / whan the fader of heuen ſent downe his ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne to take fleſſhe &amp; blode of our lady ſaynt Mary &amp; to be borne of her for our ſaluacyon / In that tyme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour of Rome Octauian helde the empyre of all the worlde / In the yere of his empyre .xlij. as ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynt Luke tellyth he ſente out a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment to diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cryue all the worlde (Exiit edictu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c̈) And the diſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge was fyrſte vnder Cirinus that was byſſhopp of Syrie / And euery man went home to his owne
<pb facs="tcp:10351:7"/>countree / Thenne yede Ioſeph out of Galilce in to Nazareth in the Iewrie. and that was kynge Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids londe. the whyche cytee was callyd Bedleem. By cauſe Ioſeph was of the houſe &amp; of the meyne of kynge Dauid. therfore he yede in to his countree with his wyfe our lady ſaynt Mary grete wyth chil de / Soo whan they were there. the tyme was come that oure lady ſholde be delyuered / And ſoo ſhe was delyuered by goddys owne myghte &amp; mynyſtracyon of angelles.ſhe wrapped him in clothes &amp; layed him in a mainger. for there was none other place ¶ And ye ſhall vnderſtond that Bedleem was neuer of gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te reputaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n nor place of grete quantyte. but it hath a good fundament / For there ben many caues vnder the erthe / And Bedleem is fro Iheruſalem but two myles / It is but a caſtell. but it is callyd a cytee by cauſe kynge Dauid was borne there / And in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne was ſomtyme an hous of Yſaye that was fader to kynge Dauid. in the whyche hous kyng Dauid was borne &amp; enoynted to be kynge of Iſrael by Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>muell the prophete / And in the ſame place Cryſte was born goddis ſone of heuen / And that place was ſomtyme in the ende of a ſtrete that was callyd the Coueryd ſtrete / And this was the cauſe why it was ſoo called. for the grete heete &amp; brennynge of the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne it was ſoo coueryd wyth blacke clothes &amp; other clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes to kepe awaye the heete of the ſonne. and ſoo it is yet to this daye / And in that ſtrete was wonte to
<pb facs="tcp:10351:7"/>be a markette ones in the weke of olde clothes and other thynges. and ſpecyally of tymbre / In that ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te ſtode ſomtyme an hous. and Yſaye kyng Dauids fader lefte a lytyll hous before a denne vnder the ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. and it was ſhapen lyke a lytyll ſellar / Yſaye the fader of Dauid and other after theym putt in that caue certayn neceſſaryes that longed to houſhold for heete of the ſonne / It is alſo the mane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in alle the countree bothe in cytces and townes to be certayne houſes that ben called there Alchan. whiche we calle here Hoſtrees. and in thoſe houſes ben mules. horſes aſſes. and camelles alwaye redy yf ſoo be that ony pilgryme. marchaunt or other man that traueyle by the waye yf hym nede ony beeſt for hym or for his marchandyſe. thenne he gooth to ſuche an houſe as is callyd Alchan and there he maye hyre what beeſt that he woll haue / And thenne he gooth forth to cy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te or towne where he woll abyde. and there he dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chargeth him of his horſe or beeſt and ſendyth him in to ſuche an hous that is called Alchan / And there ben beeſtes on that manere to hyre / And the mayſter of the hous taketh the beeſt and yeueth it meete. and whan he maye he ſendyth hym home agayne there he came fro / And yf ſoo be that noo man goo in to that cyte or towne in longe tyme. he takyth the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me beeſt and ledyth hym out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne and ſettyth hym in the way hom warde / And ſo the beeſt gooth forth home w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out ony ledinge euyn to his mayſters
<pb facs="tcp:10351:8"/>hous without peryll of beeſtes or of theues / Soo eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry man that hath ony ſuche beeſtes. euery man kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth other beeſtes ben they neuer ſoo ferre aſondre / And of ſuche houſes lordes of the grounde haue gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te wynnynge &amp; tolle of ſuche beeſtes hytynge / And ſuche a manere houſe was that houſe a lytyll before or Cryſte was borne in / ¶ But abowte the byrth of Ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that hous was all dyſtroyed.ſoo that there was no thyng lefte but broken walles on euery ſyde and a lytyll caue vnder the erthe. and a lytyll vnthryfty hous tofore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> caue / &amp; there men ſolde breede in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me grounde ¶ It is alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſage in all the countree that all the breede that ſhalbe ſolde ſhall be brought in to a certayn place / And of the breede that is ſolde in the day the kynge &amp; the lorde of the grounde atte nyght ſhal haue a certen money / And whan Dauid was made kynge of Iſrael by proceſſe of tyme Ihe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruſalem was dyſtroyed and all the countree abowte Noo man toke hede of this hous by cauſe it was all dyſtroyed &amp; noo thynge lefte but that broken houſe &amp; the caue / And bredde &amp; tymbre that myght not be ſolde on the daye ſholde be putte in that hous to the next market day / Aſſes. horſe.&amp; other beeſtes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> came to the market were tyed abowte this broken hous / </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>FOr to ſpeke ayen of the matere / Whan Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauian Emperoure of Rome had ſcnte out his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment that eche man ſhold goo
<pb facs="tcp:10351:8"/>to the ſame towne that he was borne in / Thenne went Ioſeph. and our lady rode vpon an aſſe. they came ſo late wythin nyght to Bedleem as it is afo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſayd. therfore all the Innes &amp; hoſtries were ſtuffed wyth pylgrymes &amp; other men. And by cauſe they ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me in poore araye they wente abowte the cyte &amp; noo man wolde receyue theym / &amp; ſpecyally for they ſawe that our lady was a yonge woman ſyttynge vpon an aſſe heuy ſorowfull &amp; full wery. grete wyth childe and nyghe the tyme of her delyueraunce of her chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / Thenne Ioſeph ladde her in to this forſayd pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce that noo man toke hede of downe in to the lytyll derke denne / And there our lorde Iheſu Cryſte that ſame nyght was borne of our lady wythout ony diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſe of her body / In that houſe of olde tyme was lef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te a maynger of the lengthe nyghe of a fadom ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de in the walle / And by the ſame maynger was an oxe of a poore mannys tyed. And beſyde the oxe Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph tyed his aſſe / And in the ſame-mainger our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy wrapped her bleſſed ſonne in ſuche clothes as ſhe had.&amp; layed him vpon the heye tofore thoxe &amp; thaſſe For there was none other place in that countree / In oſtryes all the mayngers ben of thre or foure fete of lengthe. that an horſe or elles a nother beeſt may ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue his meete by hymſelf / And ſuche a maynger was y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that our lady laye in / </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <p>THe place where the angell apperyd to the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peherdes
<pb facs="tcp:10351:9"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nyghte that Cryſte was borne is but half a myle from Bedleem / And in that ſame pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce Dauid kepte ſhepe in his chyldhede &amp; deffended them from beers &amp; lyens &amp; other wylde beeſtes / So me bokes ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſhepeherdes of that conntree ke pe theyr ſhepe twyes in oo yere / And thoſe tymes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re whan the dayes &amp; nyghtes ben both of a lengthe And that londe abowte Bedleem is called the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of byheſt / And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place in the Eeſt is mnoſt parte mountayns. for in ſome place a man ſhall not well knowe Wynter fro Somer / And in ſome place the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re it is ryght colde.&amp; in ſome place is bothe Wynter &amp; Somer. as it is in this countree after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the places ben playne or full of hylles / For abowte ſome of the hylles a man maye fynde ſnowe in Auguſt. &amp; that ſnowe men of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> countree gadre thenne &amp; laye it in theyr caues vnder the grounde / And afterward it is borne to the markettes. and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll the lordes of the countree bye to ſet it in baſons on their borde to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke theyr drynke colde / And the poore men that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre it carye it in chaffe that the heete ſholde not mel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te it. and the lordes that bye it vncoueren it out of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chaff. thenne anone it is reſolued &amp; molte to water For comynly in that countree of the Eeſt is alwaye ſnowe in Septembre &amp; Octobre / Whan the ſonne comyth a lytyll lowe in that countree all ſedes &amp; her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bes begyn to ſprynge and were as they done in this countree in Marche &amp; Aprill / And in ſome partyes
<pb facs="tcp:10351:9"/>of the Eeſt men repe corne in Marche &amp; Aprill. but mooſt in May. after the place or ground lyeth hye or lowe / But by Bedleem ben many mo good fatte paſtures &amp; hote than in other places. in ſoo moche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> at Cryſtmaſſe barleye begynnyth to were rype. and thenne men of dyuerſe countrees ſende thether theyr horſes &amp; mules to make theym fatte / And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we calle here Cryſtmas. it is called there tyme of her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bes / ¶ And for aſmoche as whan Cryſte was borne peas was in al the worlde. therfore the angell ſayd Par hominibus bone voluntatis (And for the heete of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> countree abowte Bedleem. that is the cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhepeherdes kept theyr beeſtes there y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme of the ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. as they done yet vnto this daye / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <p>IN thoſe dayes whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment went out from Cezar Auguſt as it is aforſayde / thenne was Herode ordeyned &amp; made kynge of the londe of Iewes by the emperour &amp; by the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayns: &amp; yet was Herode noo Iewe ne kyng of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes borne / But by cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame emperour &amp; the Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maynes had made ſubgette to theym the londe of Iewery &amp; many of the prouynces abowte theym vn to Inde Perſe &amp; Caldee. ſo by ſtrong honde they ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de hym kynge / And all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> countree knewe well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> He rode was but a lyon &amp; neuer came of kyngis blood. ne of Iewry bore. but made kyng by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour &amp; Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mayns.ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prophecie of daniel ſhold be fulfylled
<pb facs="tcp:10351:10"/>in the tyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the byrthe of Cryſte. whan he ſayd) Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> venerit ſanctus ſacto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>rum</ex>
                  </expan> &amp;c̈ (as it is aforſayde / Yet the Iewes contynuynge in theyr malyce &amp; falſneſſe ſayde. that longe tyme after the Natiuite of Cryſte their vncco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n ſeſſed not. but that they had many kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges after / But yet the falſe Iewes forſake not that Herode came of a Iewe on the fader ſyde &amp; of a Pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nym of the moders ſyde. &amp; ſo he was noo very Iewe Wherfore cryſten men make the Iewes vtterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuled of the prophecye of Iacob theyr Patryarke. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd thus) Non auferetur ceptru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de iuda nec dux de femore cius doner veniat qui mittendꝰ eſt et ip<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e erit expectaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> genciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that is to ſaye / The ſeptie of Iuda ſhall not be borne away ne the ſtocke of lygnage tyl he come that ſhall be ſente. and he ſhall be that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ſhall abyde / ¶ And many other queſtyons of the Iewes to the cryſten men of the vncco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of theyr kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <p>WHan god was borne of our lady as it is afor ſayd thenne this ſterre that was prophecied by Balaam. and long tyme abyden and lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked after by the twelue Aſtronomers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd hyll of Vaws / ¶ The ſame nyghte and the ſame houre that god was borne. the ſame ſterre began to ryſe in manere of the ſonne ſhynynge bryghte / And after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fourme of an egle aſcended aboue the hylle / And all the daye in the higheſt place of the ayre it abode w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out ony meuynge / Soo whan the ſonne was mooſt
<pb facs="tcp:10351:10"/>hote and mooſt highe there was no dyfference in ſhi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge betwyx the ſterre &amp; the ſonne / Neuertheles ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me bokes ſayen. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the ſame daye whan god was borne. were ſeen many ſonnes. but whan the daye of Cryſtmas was paſte. the ſterre aſcended vp in to the fyrmament / And the ſterre that thus was ſhewed was noo thynge lyke the ſterres that ben paynted he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re in dyuerſe places / For it had ryght many ſtrakes and beemys more bryght brennynge than a bronde of fyre / And as an Egle fleenge &amp; betynge the ayre with his wynges. ryght ſoo the ſtrakes &amp; the beemes of that mouyd themſelfe abowte / And the ſterre had in hymſelf the fourme &amp; the likneſſe of a yonge chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. and aboue hym the ſygne of a Croſſe / And a voy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce was herde in the ſterre ſayenge) Natus eſt nobis hodie rex iudeo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>rum</ex>
                  </expan> qui eſt expectaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> genciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor eo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>rum</ex>
                  </expan> ite ad inquirendum eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; adorandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that is to ſaye / This daye is borne to vs kynge of the Iewes that folke haue abyden and he is lorde of them god forth and ſeke hym and doo hym worſhypp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for ſtrengthynge of our fayth &amp; to afferme thys matere forſayd almyghty god whoſe prouydence in his ordynaunce fayllyth not / ¶ And ſaynt Poul ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yth) Vocatea que non ſunt tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ea que ſunt) that is to ſaye / God callyth thoſe that ben not aſwell as thoſe that ben of his prouidence / Thus he dyde and dyſpoſed. as he dyde in the olde Teſtamente. whan he gaaf a langage to an aſſe. and made an aſſe to
<pb facs="tcp:10351:11"/>ſpeke to Balaam / He wolde in the begyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nynge of the newe Teſtament yeue a voyce to ſpeke out of a ſterie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame Balaam prophecyed of / ¶ Whan al the people of that countree abowteſawe this won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derfull and merueyllous ſterre. and alſo herde the vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ys of the ſterre. they were gretly affrayed. and hadde grete wonder therof / But they knewe well that it was the ſame ſterre that was prophecied of by Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam. and longe tyme was deſyred and abyden of all the people of that countree theraboute.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <p>Thus whan thyſe thre Kynges that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme regned in Ynde. Caldee and Perſidie weren enfourmed and well aſſured by the Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mers and by the prophecyes of this ſterre / They we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ryght gladde that they had grace to ſe that ſterre in theyr dayes that was longe tyme prophecyed afo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. and all the people had ſo longe loked after / Whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>refore though eche of thyſe thre kynges weren ferre from other. and none of theym knewe of others pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe. yet in one houre the ſterre appered to theym all thre / And thenne they ordeyned and purpoſed theim anone wyth grete and ryche gyftes and many dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe ornamentes that were belongynge vnto the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gree &amp; araye of kynges. and alſo wyth mules &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels and horſes charged wyth precyouſe treſours &amp; wyth grete nombre and multytude of people to goo ſeke in theyr beſte arraye and to worſhippe our lorde
<pb facs="tcp:10351:11"/>Iheſu Cryſte that was borne to be Sauiour of all the worlde and the kynge of Iewes that was born that tyme. as the voyce of the ſterre ſpake and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched / And ferthermore they arayed theym moche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more honeſtely and worthyly / For they knewe well and vnderſtode that he was a more worthyer kynge than ony of all the worlde / ¶ Ferthermore eche of thyſe thre bleſſyd kynges had wyth theym grete ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryage of oxen and ſhepe and other beeſtes that lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge to mannys lyuynge and ſuſtenaunce. and other manere thynges neceſſary belongynge to the offyce of a chamber. kechen and to all other offyces belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge to a kynges aſtate. &amp; alſo bothe fode for man &amp; beeſt they caryed wyth theim / In ſomoche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ordeyned ſoo grete plentee that ſholde ſuffyſe theim well bothe outwarde &amp; homwarde / And euery kyng had people as it had be an hoſte / ¶ It is the mane<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re in that countree of the Eeſst oute take cytees. that in other townes ben many fayr Oſtries. and for the mooſt party al maneze vytaylles both for man &amp; beſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te is ynough for the comyn people. but not for ſuche kynges &amp; ſuche grete lordes that ryde wyth ſoo gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te multytude. Beddyng &amp; ſuche other neceſſaries of chambers. neyther of chapell. ne of kechin is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fycyent ne honeſt &amp; therfore lordes haue ſuche caria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age wyth theim / And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countree for the moſt par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty men ryde or go by nyght for bren<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ynge of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e &amp; in heete of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day they reſt / Ye ſhal vnd<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>ſtonde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there
<pb facs="tcp:10351:12"/>ben thre Indes. of whom thiſe thre lordes were kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges / And alle thoſe londes for the mooſt partye ben yles / There ben alſo thre grete waters and thre gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te deſertes or wylderneſſes full of wylde &amp; peryllouſe beeſtes and horryble ſerpentes / And in that countree doon growe alſo thiſe longe grete redes that ben bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ught in to Englonde. and ſome ben ſoo grete y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men make houſes and ſhyppes of theym / And eche yle is deuided and departed eche from other / And eche lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de is full of wylde beeſtes / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <p>IN the fyrſt Ynde is the londe of Nubie. and therof Melchior was Kynge whan Cryſte was born / And there is alſo the <abbr>lond</abbr> of Ara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bie / And in that londe is the mount Sinay / A man out of the redde ſee maye lightly ſaylle out of Egyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and Syrie in to Ynde / ¶ And pylgrymes &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chauntes that from Ynde paſſen the redde ſee.ſayen that al the grounde of the redde ſee is ſoo redde that the water aboue ſemyth as it were redde wyne. not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wythſtondyng that water is as other water is of co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lour. and it is merueyllouſly ſalte / And it is ſoo clere that in the deppeſt of all the water men maye ſe fyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhes and dyſcerne al thynges by the botom<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſee And that water is thre cornerde. and it ebbyth and floweth in to the grete ſee of Occean. and is foure or fiue myles of brede where it is brodeſt / And there the chyldern of Iſrael yede thrugh with drye fete whan
<pb facs="tcp:10351:12"/>Pharao &amp; his hoſt purſued theim. and al were drow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned man &amp; beeſt / Out of that ſee ſourdeth a grete flo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de that rennyth in to a ryuer of paradyſe terreſtre.&amp; that ryuer is callyd Nilus / And this Nilus paſſyth by Egypte, and by it cometh moche ryche marchan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyſe out of Ynde and ſoo paſſeth in to Egypte. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Babilonie.&amp; Aliſaundre. and ſoo thorugh al the worlde / And all the erthe of the londe of Arabie the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re the mount Synai is. is merueyllouſly redde / Sto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes &amp; trees. herbes and all other thynges that growe there ben redde for the mooſt partye / And there is fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unde golde wonderfully redde in manere of thinne &amp; ſmalle rotes. and that is the beſte golde of the worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ¶ There is alſo an hyll that is called Bona. and in that hyll is founde the ſtone that is callyd Sma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragdus / And that is cutte out wyth grete crafte and grete traueyle of the hylle. And that hyll is kepte be ſyly &amp; ſtrongly wyth the Sowdans meyne / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <p>IN the ſecond Ynde was the lond of Godolie and therof was Balthaſar kyng whan Criſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te was borne / And he offred enſence to Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu / And there was alſo of olde tyme in that londe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kyngdom of Saba / And in that londe growith mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re plente of good ſpyces than in al the londes of the Eeſt after / And in eſpecyall enſence more than in al the worlde / And it droppyth out of certayne trees in manere of gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me / </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10351:13"/>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <p>IN the thyrd Ynde was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyngdom of Ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ars. and in the tyme of Cryſtis byrthe Iaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per was kynge therof / And he offred to god Myrre / And that londe is called thyle of Egriſ will / In that yle groweth more myrre than in all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de after / And it wexyth lyke eeres of corne that were brente wyth the weder and it growyth ryght thycke And whan it is rype it is ſo ſofte that it cleuyth on mennes clothes as they goon by the waye / And then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men take ſmalle cordes &amp; girdles and drawe theim all abowte the eeres. and ſoo the myrre cleuyth on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cordes and on the girdles. and afterwarde the myrre is wronge out of the cordes and girdles / ¶ Wherfore we maye vnderſtonde that this was doon of a gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te prouydence of the grete mercy of god : that thyſe thre kynges Melchior Balthazar and Iaſper of thyſe londes in whom thyſe good and ryche gyftes wexed and-growyd that ſholde be offred to god by the olde prophecies / Rather they maye be callyd kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges than kynges of other grete londes. wherof ſayth Dauid the prophete) Beges tharſis &amp; inſule mune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra offerent reges arabum &amp; ſaba dona domino deo adducent) that is to ſaye / Kynges of Taars and of the yle ſhall offre gyftes kynges of Arabie &amp; of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ba ſhall brynge gyftes to our lorde god / ¶ Somty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me thyſe kynges had other names / Melchior was called kinge of Nubie &amp; of Arabie / Balthazar was called kyng of Golie &amp; Saba.&amp; Iaſper was called
<pb facs="tcp:10351:13"/>kynge of Taars &amp; of thyle of Egriſ will / &amp; it was called the kyngdom of Taars bicauſe it was nexed to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame yle / And ſo the names of their kingdoms ben ſpecifyed in ſpecyall for dyfference of other cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees and yles of the countree / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <p>TO ſhewe ayen of thiſe thre worſhypful kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. of the araye and ordenaunce wyth ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che treſour and ornamentes and wyth gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te multytude of people as it is aforſayd / And whan they rode forth out of their kyngdoms none of them wyſt ne knewe of others purpoos by cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> long waye that was bytwyx eche kyngdom. yet the ſterre went euenly tofore thiſe thre kynges &amp; al theyr mey ne / And whan theiſtode ſtyll or reſted then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſterre ſtode ſtyll.&amp; whan they yede or rode the ſterre alway yede forth tofore them in his vertu &amp; ſtrength &amp; yaue lyght to al the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r wayes / And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme was peas in al the worlde. wherfore in al cytees &amp; townes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ye de by was no gate ſhyt nyght nor day. but it ſemyd to thoſe thre kynges &amp; to al theyr people y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer daye &amp; neuer nyght in all thoſe .xiij. dayes / whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all men of cytees &amp; townes that thyſe thre kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges came by were wond<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>ly aferde &amp; merueyled therof For they ſawe kynges with ſomoche people &amp; beſtes &amp; caryage that paſſyd by theym in grete haſt in the nyghte / But they knewe not what they were ne from what place they came. ne whyther they ſholde
<pb facs="tcp:10351:14"/>goo / But on the morowe they ſawe the waygretely defoylled and traced wyth hors fete &amp; other beeſtes / Wherfore they were in grete doubte what it ſhold be and grete altercaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n was amonge theym in that co untree longe tyme after / ¶ Soo ferthermore whan thyſe thre kynges had rydden thrugh dyuers londes kyngdoms. citees. and townes. they rode ouer hylles waters. valeyes. playnes. and many other dyuers pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryllouſe places wythoute ony dyſeſe or lettynge / For all the waye that they rode were it highe or lowe all ſemyd to theym euyn and playne and fayre waye / ¶ They toke neuer herberough by the waye nyghte nor daye ne neuer reſted themſelf but to make water neyther their beeſtes that were in theyr company. ne neyther ete nor dranke after the tyme that they had take their waye tyll they came in to Bedleem / And all thyſe .xiij dayes Iourneyes ſemyd theym but one daye / And thus thorugh the grete myghte of god &amp; the ledynge of the ſterre they came in to Iheruſalem the thyrtenth daye after that Cryſte was borne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpryſynge of the ſonne. wherof this is noo doubte / For they founde oure lady and her ſone in the ſame place and in the caue that Criſte was borne in / &amp; he was layed in an olde maynger ¶ Alſo many bokes telle that they came in to Iheruſalem and to Bed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leem in the in the myddes of the daye. wherof ſaynt Gregory ſayth thus in an Omelie) Si dimna opera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cio humana racione comprehendi poſſet non eſſet
<pb facs="tcp:10351:14"/>admirabilis. nec haberet fides meritum cui humana raco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prebet experimentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that is to ſaye / Yf the wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of god mighte be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended in mannes wytte or reaſon it were noo wonder: for fayth hath no me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de where kynde reaſon ſhewyth if to man / ¶ For ou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re lorde god that in the olde Teſtament ledde Aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kuc the prophete by one heere of his heed out of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye in to Babilonie &amp; Caldee. that was a hundred dayes Iourneye bitwene goynge &amp; comynge to Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyel the prophete that was in a pytte among wylde lyens. and anone reſtored the ſame Abakuc in to his owne place ayen / The ſame lorde god in the newe Teſtament was myghty to lede &amp; brynge thiſe thre worſhipfull kynges out of theyr kyngdoms in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eeſt in to the londe of Iewery in twelue dayes wythoute ony dyſeſe or lettynge / ¶ Alſo our lorde Iheſu Cryſt after his reſurrexcyon yede to his dyſcyples in to an houſe wythout openynge of gate or locke / And as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre brente not ne dyde none harme to the thre chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren whan they were putte in the furneys of fire. ne noo ſauour of ſmoke was founde in theym / Ryght ſoo in the tyme of thyſe thre gloryous kynges our la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy ſaynt Mary bare our lorde Iheſu Cryſt that was and is very god &amp; man / And yet ſhe was tofore and euer after a clene mayde / God almyghty myght ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rue brought thiſe thre kynges &amp; al their folke out of the Eeſt in to Iewerye in a moment as he broughte Abakuc the prophete forſayde / But though god al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty
<pb facs="tcp:10351:15"/>made hymſelf lowe and was borne in gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te pouerte and toke vpon him manhode &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eltee. yet he wolde merueyllouſly ſhewe his byrth to all the worlde. in heuen &amp; in erthe wyth the myghte of his godheed &amp; of his hyghe mageſte / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <p>WHan thyſe thre kynges eche in his waye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his hoſte &amp; companye were almoſt come to Iheruſalem ſaue two myle / Thenne a der<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke &amp; a grete clowde couered theym &amp; alle the erthe / And in that derke clowde they loſte theyr ſterre as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophecye of Yſaye ſayd) Surge illuminare <abbr>Ihrlm</abbr> quia venit lumen tnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et gloria dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i ſuper te orta eſt quia ecce tenebre operient terram &amp; caligo populos) that is to ſay / Iheruſalem aryſe and take lyght for thy lyghte is come to the &amp; the Ioye of god is ſpron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gen vpon the. for loo. derkneſſe ſhall couere the erthe and a clowde the people / ¶ Whan thyſe thre kynges were nyghe Iheruſalem. thenne Mechior kynge of Nubie &amp; of Arabie wyth his people was faſt by the hyll of Caluarie there Cryſt was doon on the croſſe by the wyll of god. there he abode in the clowde &amp; in derkneſſe / And that tyme the hyll of Caluarie was a roche of twelue grees of heyghte / And on this hyll theues and other men for dyuers treſpaces were put to theyr dethe / There was alſo beſyde this hyll an hyghe way. and to that highe waye were thre highe wayes metynge togyder / And ſoo for derkneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10351:15"/>clowde. and for they knewe not the way they abode there &amp; yede no ferther at that tyme / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <p>AFter that Melchior was thus come. thenne nexte hym a lytyll vnder the clowde came kynge Balthazar that was kinge of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolie and of Saba with all his hoſte. and abode be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde the mount of Caluarie in a lytyll towne why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is called Galilee / And holy wrytte ſpekyth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of that towne / For the diſcyples of god almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before his reſurreccyon and after alſo were wonte alwaye to come thyther togider / In that towne god almyghty appered to his diſcyples after his reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion / As it is wreten in the goſpell (Precedet vos in galileam ibi eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> videbitis) that is / He ſhall goo tofo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re you in to Galilee and there ye ſhal ſe him ¶ But there is a londe that is called Galilee. and that is a grete lordſhypp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. and it is thre dayes Iourneye from Iheruſalem / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <p>ANd whan thiſe .ij. kynges Melcheor &amp; Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thazar were com<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; taryed in thiſe places for ſayd in the clowde &amp; derknes. thenne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de wexed clere. but the ſterre appered not / Soo whan thiſe .ij. kynges ſawe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were nye <abbr>Ihrlm</abbr> though neyther of them knew other. they toke their way to warde the cyte / And-they mette togyder beſyde the mount of Caluarie there as thre wayes were metyng
<pb facs="tcp:10351:16"/>togyder / Thenne came the kynge Iaſper kyng of Taars &amp; of the yle of Egryſwyll wyth all his ooſt. And ſoo thyſe thre gloryous kynges wyth alle theyr meyne. caryage &amp; beeſtes mette togyder in this hyhe waye / And notwythſtondyng that none of theim ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer before had ſeen other. ne none of them knewe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers perſones. ne knewe of others comynge. yet atte theyr metynge eche of theym anone ryght wyth gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce Ioye &amp; reuerence kyſſed other / And though they were of dyuers langages. yet eche of them to theyr ſe mynge ſpake one manere of ſpeche / Soo whan they had ſpoken togyder. &amp; eche of theym had tolde hys Iourney &amp; the cauſe of his waye / Alle theyr cauſes were acordynge in to one / Thenne were they moche the gladder &amp; the more feruente in theyr waye.&amp; ſoo they rode forth / And ſodenly at the vpryſynge of the ſonne they came in to the cyte of Iheruſalem / And whan they knewe that Iheruſalem was the kinges cytee the whyche theyr predeceſſoures &amp; the Caldees of olde tyme had byſeged &amp; diſtroyed. they were ful glad. ſuppoſing to haue founde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge Iheſu there borne in the ſame cyte / ¶ And that tyme was Hero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de in Iheruſalem / &amp; he &amp; all the cyte were gretly dyſ trowbled of theyr ſodenly comynge / For theyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany &amp; theyr beeſtes were of ſoo grete nombre &amp; ſoo grete multitude that the cyte myght not receyue the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ym / But for the mooſt partye laye wythout the cyte al aboute / Wherof Yſayas prophecied &amp; ſayd) Eorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo
<pb facs="tcp:10351:16"/>gencium venerit tibi inundacio camello<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abrum"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>rum</ex>
                  </expan> operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et te dromedarij madian &amp; effa. omnes de ſaba veni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent auru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; thus deferentes &amp; laudem dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o annuncian tes) that is to ſaye / The ſtrength of folke cometh to the Iheruſalem grete plente of camelles ſhall coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. the dromedaries of Madian &amp; of Effa ſhall com<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the. many folke ſhall come fro Saba bryngyng golde &amp; enſence and yeuynge laude to god / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <p>THis Herode was ordeyned kinge by the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour &amp; by the Romaynes. and he was but yonge of aege. and was that tyme in his pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>layes in Iheruſalem / And thenne thyſe thre kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aſked in that cyte of the people where that chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de was borne. wherof ſpeketh in the goſpell theuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt) Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> natus eſſet ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp;c̈) that is to ſay / Whan god was born in Bedleem in the cyte of Iewery in the dayes of Herode kynge of the ſame londe. thre kynges came oute of the Eeſt &amp; ſayd) Where is he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is borne the kynge of Iewes. we ſawe his ſterre in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eeſt and we be come to worſhyppe hym (And Hero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de herde this and he was dyſtourbled &amp; all Iheruſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lem wyth hym / And he gadred togyder all the pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces &amp; the preeſtes. and aſked of theym where Cryſte ſholde be borne / And they ſayd. in Bedleem of Iew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry. thus it is wreten by the prophete) Thou Bedie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em londe of Iewery thou arte not lyfyll amonge the prynces of Iewery. of the ſhall goo out a duke that
<pb facs="tcp:10351:17"/>ſhall rule my people of Iſrael (Thenne Herode pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely called to him the thre kynges &amp; lerned of them the tyme of the ſterre that apperyd to theym. and ſo ſente theim forthe in to Bedleem.&amp; ſayd) Goo and enquyte beſely of this childe. and whan ye haue fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde hym come telle me that I may goo &amp; worſhyp hym (whan they had herde the kynge they yede the yr way / And the ſterre that they ſawe in the Eeſt ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de before theym tyll they came there the chylde was And whan they ſawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſterre thei were right gladde And they yede in to the hous and openyd theyr tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours. and offred to hym. golde. enſence.&amp; myrre / All this is the goſpell / And in theyr ſlepe an aungell ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me fro god &amp; badde theym that they ſholde not goo ayen to Herode / And ſoo they torned home to theyr countree by a nother waye / ¶ Of thyſe thre kynges why they cam<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fyrſt in to Iheruſalem rather than in to Bedleem many bokes in dyuers manere declare / and many cauſes ben wreten whyche were to longe to telle / But amonge all other cauſes one is. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge Herode &amp; the Cyteyzyns were ſoo diſtrowbled for theyr ſoden comynge. and alſo they ſeenge that thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe lordes were kynges. and theyr hoſte came oute of Caldee &amp; oute of the Eeſt. the whyche of olde tyme thrugh ſuffraunce of god had oft tymes purſued the yr kynge and beſegyd &amp; diſtroyed the cyte of <abbr>Ihrlm</abbr> &amp; that londe abowte / A nother for they came fro ſoo ferre countices to worſhyp the kynge of Iewes that
<pb facs="tcp:10351:17"/>was latly borne / And by cauſe that Herode was but an ſtraunger and was made kyng by the emperour &amp; the Romaynes. he was aferde leeſt he ſholde haue loſte his kyngdom by cauſe that Cryſte was borne / Alſo a nother cauſe was chiſe thre ky<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges of goddis ordenaunce came ſoo to Iheruſalem wythout auyſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment whan they had loſte theyr ſterre / For Iheruſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lem was the kynges cyte. and alwaye the kinges of the londe were mooſt abydynge there. and doctours of the lawe &amp; the Scrybes with theyr ſcriptures and prophecyes were euermore preſent in that cyte / So y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes and the Scrybes knewe well longe tyme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. cryſte ſholde be borne in that place / ¶ Wherfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re Iewes maye neuer ſhewe cauſe to excuſe theim of theyr falſe byleue / Of this ſayth ſaynt Gregory in his Omelie) Iudeos profecto. bene yſaac cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iacob ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lium ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> benediceret preſignauif. qui caligans ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis &amp; prophetizans in preſenti filiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non vidit cui ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in poſterum multu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preuidit &amp;c̈) that is to ſaye / By this we maye vnderſtonde the Iewes. for Yſaac whan he was blynde and myghte not ſe he bleſſyd Iacob his ſone and prophecyed of hym / And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer whan he had him in his preſence before hym he ſawe hym not / And yet he ſawe in ſpyryte many thinges whiche ſholde falle to hym afterwarde / In lyke manere ſo the Iewes were gretely ful of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpyri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of prophecye / But hym that they prophecyed of whan they had him among theym they knewe him
<pb facs="tcp:10351:18"/>not. For they diſpyſed hym whan he was born / And longe tyme tofore they prophecyed of his byrth. and not oonly that he ſholde be borne. but in what place he ſholde be borne they tolde to Herode / ¶ So theyr knowynge &amp; theyr prophecye ſhall bere wytneſſe to theyr dampnaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n and vs helpe of our byleue &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe of oure ſaluacyon / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <p>Whan thyſe thre kynges were enfourmed by Herode &amp; by the doctours of the lawe of the byrthe of Cryſte. and of the place where he was borne &amp; were paſſed out of the cyte of Iheruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem / Thenne the ſterre appered to theim agayne as it dyde before. and ſoo it yede forth before theim tyll they came in to Bedleem. whiche is but two myles fro Iheruſalem / And faſte by that place as it is afo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſayd were the ſhepeherdes to whom the angell ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pered wyth grete lyghte &amp; ſhewed to theym the byr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the of Cryſte / And thyſe thre kynges rode by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me place there the ſhepeherdes were and ſpake wyth them / And whan the ſhepeherdes ſawe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſterre they ranne togyder. and ſayd that in ſuche a lyghte &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che a clereneſſe an angell appered to to theym &amp; told theym of the byrthe of Cryſte and alle that the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell ſayd to theym / And al that they had herde &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en they tolde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges. wherof the kynges were rig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hte gladde. and with good chere toke grete conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of the ſhepeherdes wordes / And ſo of wytneſſe of the ſhepeherdes &amp; of the voyce of the aungell that
<pb facs="tcp:10351:18"/>apperyd in the ſterre and was herde the kynges had doubte of no thyng / ¶ Some bokes in the Eeſt ſaye that voyce that was herde oute of the ſterre was the voyce of the ſame angell that ſhewed the byrthe of Cryſte bothe to the ſhepeherdes and to the kynges / ¶ They ſaye alſo in the Eeſt that the Iewes bileue in that the angell that yede before-the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rael w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a pylar of fyre whan they yede out of Egip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te. that ſame angell it was whoos voyce was herde in the ſterre. and that yede ſo forth wyth the ſterre be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the thre kynges / For whan the thre kynges ſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke wyth the ſhepeherdes. the ſterre more &amp; more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ſhyne bryghter &amp; bryghter ¶ Thyſe thre kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges were the fyrſte of myſcreauntes that byleued on Cryſte. and the ſhepeherdes were the firſte of Iewes that byleuyd on Cryſte / And all though the kynges were noo Iewewes yet they ſayde that they came to worſhyppe the kynge of Iewes / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <p>WHan the kynges had ſpoken wyth the ſhepe herdes. thenne they gaaf theim grete gyftes and ſoo rode forth to Bedleem / Thenne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none as they were come vnto Bedleem they lighted downe of theyr horſes &amp; chaunged theyr araye. and clothed theym in the beſte and rycheſt clothes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they hadde / And as kinges ſholde be arayed they arayed themſelfe / And alwayes the ſterre yede forth tofore theim / And the nerer that they came to the place the
<pb facs="tcp:10351:19"/>more the ſterre ſhyned bryghter and bryghter / And thenne they rode thorugh the Coueryd ſtrete as it is tolde afore tyll they came to the lytyll hous where in Crſte was borne / And the ſterre ſtode ſtyll vpon the grounde tofore the door / And anone after the ſterre departed hymſelf in ſoo grete lyghte. that the lytyll hous &amp; the caue wythin was full of lyghte / And ſoo anone the ſterre aſcended vp in to the ayre. and the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſtode ſtyll alwaye in the ſame place. as it is ſayde in the goſpell tofore (Et intrantes domum &amp;c̈) And entrynge in to the houſe they founde our lady &amp; her chylde. and fell downe and worſhipped hym and of fred to hym gyftes. Golde. Myrre. and Enſence / ¶ Of this came afterward an vſe in that countree of the Eeſt / There ſhal noo man come in the preſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of the Soudan. or of a kynge to ſpeke wyth hym but he haue golde or ſyluer or ſome other rycheſſe in his hondes / And alſo or he ſpeke wyth the Soudan he ſhall kyſſe the grounde / And this is vſed in that countree vnto this daye / ¶ Ferthermore frere Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urs whan they ſhall come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Soudan or to a kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge they muſt offre to hym peeres or apples / For they maye towche no golde nor ſyluer / And the Soudan receyuyth the peeres or apples wyth reuerence &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſſe / ¶ And that tyme that thiſe thre kynges of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feed thus to Cryſte. he was in his manhede. a lytyll chylde of .xiij. dayes of aege / And he laye wrappyd in clothes of lytyll valewe in his moders lappe / 
<pb facs="tcp:10351:19"/>¶ As it is wreten in dyuerſe bokes ſhe was in perſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne fleſſhly. and ſomwhat browne / And in preſence of thyſe thre kynges ſhe was couered wyth a poore whyte mantell. and that ſhe helde cloſe tofore her wyth her lyfte honde / And her heed was couered all togyder ſaue her face wyth a lynnen cloth / And ſhe ſate vpon the maynger / And wyth her ryght honde ſhe helde vp god almyghtys heed / Soo after thyſe thre kynges had worſhypped god &amp; kyſſed his hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ryght deuowtly. and layed theyr gyftes beſyde Cryſtys heed. what was done wyth thyſe gyftes ye ſhall here afterwarde / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <p>MElchior kyng of Nubie and of Arabie that offred golde to god: he was leeſt of ſtature &amp; of perſone / And Balthazar that was kyng of Godolie &amp; of Saba that offryd enſence. he was of a meane ſtature / And Iaſper that was kynge of Taars and of thyle of Egriſwill that offred myrre he was mooſt of ſtature. and he was a blacke Ethy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>opye wythout doubte / ¶ For the prophete ſayd) Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram illo procident ethiopes &amp; inimici eius terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent venient ad te qui detrahebant tibi &amp; adorabunt veſtigia &amp;c̈) that is to vnderſtond / Byfore hym ſhal falle and bowe downe Ethiopies. and his enmyes ſhall lycke the erthe. they ſhall come to the that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrahyd the. and they ſhall worſhippe the ſteppes of thy fete / ¶ But hauynge regarde to the perſones y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10351:20"/>were that tyme they were but lytyll perſones thoos thre kynges. in ſoo moche that all manere of people had moche merueylle therof / And that ſemyd well y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were come from ferce countrees / For the nerer the Eeeſt and the vpryſynge of the ſonne that men ben born the leſſe they ben of ſtature. and the more fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble &amp; tender. and herbes ben the hoter and ſerpentes and ſuche wormes and peryllous beeſtes ben the gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter and the more venemous / And all other beeſtes &amp; fowles ben there more grete than here / ¶ Alſo thyle kynges broughte wyth theym many ryche gyftes &amp; ornamentes that kynge Aliſaunder whyche conque<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryd all the worlde lefte in Ynde and in Caldee and in Perſe. and alle the ornamentes that the quene of Saba founde in Salamons Temple. and dyuerſe veſſell that were of the kinges hous and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of god in Iheruſalem / The whyche in the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of dyſtruccyon of Iheruſalem were borne in to the countrees &amp; londes by theym of Perſe &amp; of Cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee / And many other Iewelles bothe of golde &amp; ſyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer and precyous ſtones thyſe kynges brought wyth theym &amp; offred to god / </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>BVt whan thei founde our lorde Cryſt Iheſu layed in that Cribbe &amp; in poore clothes. and the ſterre had yeue ſoo grete lyghte in all the place there Cryſt was that it ſemed as they had ſton de in a furnays of fyre. they were ſo ſore aferde. that
<pb facs="tcp:10351:20"/>of all thoſe ryche Iewels and ornamentes that they brought w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theim they toke noo thyng out of their coffres but that came nexte theyr hondes. as it was the wyll of oure lorde / ¶ And Melchior toke out of his treſory a rounde appyll of golde as moche as a man myghte holde in his honde &amp; .xxx. gylte pence.&amp; that he offred to god / Bathazar kynge of Godolie &amp; of Saba toke out of his treſour enſence as it cam<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> next to his honde &amp; he offred that to god / Iaſper as it came to his honde offred myrre to god wyth we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng teeres / Soo thyſe thre kynges were ſoo aferde &amp; ſoo deuowte in theyr offrynge. that of all the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des that our lady ſayd that tyme thei toke but lytyl conſyderaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n / Saue oonly to euery kynge as thei of fred to god ſhe bowed downe wyth her heed. and ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yd mekely) Deo gracias) that is to ſaye / Thankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be to god / ¶ Thappyll of golde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Melchior of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fryd wyth the .xxx. pence was ſomtyme kynge Aly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunders the grete conquerour / And he dyde make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame appyll of ſmall peces of golde that he had ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred of the trybute of all the worlde / And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he bare alway in his honde / And this appyll was left in Yn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de whan he was comen fro Paradyſe wyth many other ryche Iewels / ¶ Morouer it is the manere of that countree of the Eeſt whan a Soudan or a kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge paſſeth thrugh a cyte. thenne euery man after his power is tofore his owne door hall caſte enſence and myrre in a fire / &amp; what man dooth it not he is hold
<pb facs="tcp:10351:21"/>a rebell ayenſt the Soudan or kynge. for therto is ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke good hede / And this vſage in all the Eeſt betoke nyth newe ſubiecco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n &amp; dayly obedyence both to god &amp; to theyr mawmettes. or to a king whether if is do ne to / Alſo in olde tyme Martyrs were not on<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtreyned to worſhyppe mawmettes. but alſo to wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyppe theym wyth enſence &amp; fyre / And this maner<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sarrazyns aſke. alway of Cryſten men that ben in theyr pryſon for to come in to theyr Temple of the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yr goddes. &amp; worſhypfully to doo ſacrefyce to theyr mawmettes wyth fyre &amp; enſence / </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <p>WHan almyghty god lowed &amp; meked hymſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe &amp; became man for our ſaluacyon. &amp; was borne of the bleſſyd moder Mary. yet he had noo nede of gyftes of the thre kynges / Neuertheleſſe the rounde appyll of golde that was offred to hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anone as kynge Melchior had offred it. it was in a moment al broken in to duſte / ¶ So we ſhall vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtonde in fygure as the ſtone that was kytte oute of the hyll wythout mannys honde or ony Inſtrument and brake an horrible mawmette vnto duſte &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der. the whyche the kynge Nabugodonoſar ſawe in his ſlepe / Ryght ſoo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtone. that is to ſaye. our lorde Iheſu Cryſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out ony corrupco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of ſynne was bor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne in to this worlde / The appyll that betokenyth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde thrugh his mekeneſſe &amp; his vertue &amp; the ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yngth of his godhede in a moment he brake alle to
<pb facs="tcp:10351:21"/>noughte / ¶ What befell of thyſe yeftes ye maye he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re afterwarde / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <p>AS thiſe .iij. kynges had thꝰ perfourmed their waye &amp; theyr offrynge &amp; done all thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they came fore. thenne as mankynde axyth &amp; wolde they &amp; theyr meyne.&amp; their horſes &amp; beeſtes began to ete &amp; drinke &amp; ſlepe. and all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> daye they to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke their reſte &amp; playſur in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> towne of Bedleem / For as it is tolde before they ne ete ne dranke. in all thoſe xiij. dayes / And thenne they tolde mekely to men of Bedleem of theyr countrees. &amp; how merueyllouſly they came thyd<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> by ledynge of the ſterre fro y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ferdeſt parte of the worlde / &amp; Ferd<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>more as the goſpel ſayth Et reſponſo accepto in ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnis ne redirent ad herode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per alia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viam reuerſi ſunt in regione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay The angel of god warned the thre kynges in theyr ſlepe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſholde not torne ayen to Herode. &amp; ſo by a nother waye they yede home to theyr kyngdoms / But y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſterre that yede afore theym appered no more after / And ſo thyſe .iij. kynges yede all homwardes togider in to theyr owne countrees w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grefe Ioye &amp; honour.&amp; they rode forth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all theyr caryage &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple thrugh al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> londes &amp; prouinces y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Olifernes had of olde tyme / And for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of people men of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countree demed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Olifernes to be come thyd<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> ayen.&amp; whan they came in to ony towne or Cyte they were receyued worſhypfully of alle the people / ¶ And
<pb facs="tcp:10351:22"/>moreouer they prechyd &amp; tolde to the people as they rode all that they had ſeen and herde. And ſoo well payed for theyr vytaylles and ſpake ſo mekely and goodly that theyr names and theyr prayſynge was neuer after forgoten / ¶ But the way that they had rydden to Bedleem warde in .xiij. dayes thorugh le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge and conduytyng of the ſterre. they myght vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ryde and goo ayen in two yeres / And that was done for men ſholde knowe what dyfference was be twene goddys might &amp; mannys power &amp; werkyng / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <p>WHan Herode and all the Scrybes and other people herde telle that thyſe thre kynges we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re goon home agayn and were not come to hym as he badde theim. thenne wyth grete enuye &amp; malyce he purſued after theym a grete waye / And al way as he rode after the kynges he herde all the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple bleſſe theym &amp; prayſe theym. and ſpeke of theyr nobleſſe / Wherfore this Herode brent &amp; dyſtroyed al all the londe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the thre kynges had rode by.&amp; ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally theim of Taars &amp; Silicie. For he put vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had ſuffred them preuely to paſſe there o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſee.&amp; therfore he brent all theyr ſhyppes &amp; to he all their good / Alſo he &amp; his Scribes purſued thy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe kynges w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> grete enuie. for they herde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people tell how wond<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>ly they came oute of theyr londes in .xiij. dayes thrugh ledyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſterre / And how they yede home ayen w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſterre or guydes or Interpretours / 
<pb facs="tcp:10351:22"/>For all manere of men that thyſe thre kynges paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſuffyſed not to tell how wonderfully they paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by theym nyghte &amp; daye / And therof Iewes that dwelled in dyuers londes &amp; places bare wytneſſe her of to Herode &amp; to all the Scribes and to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes And ſoo for the wonderfull doynge the Paynems y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had noo knowynge of holy wrytte. ne of the byrthe of Cryſte called thiſe thre kynges Magos. that is to ſaye. wytches / And the Iewes that knewe the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture &amp; the byrthe of Cryſte. and the places of enuye &amp; falſneſſe excyted the Paynems all abowte to calle theim wytches. and ſoo it was broughte in to vſage that they call thiſe thre kynges ſo yet vnto this daye and therof beryth many dyuers bokes witneſſe / But to put away all manere of doubtes and in repreuyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of all the falſe Iewes. almyghty god that is euer wonderful in his werkynge &amp; gloryous in his ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes wolde haue the preuyte of his birthe to be knowe to all the people / Soo that this gloryous name that was oonly hidde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> londe of Iewery vnto his byr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the / That ſame name all manere of naco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns thrugh all the worlde ſholde worſhypp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowe &amp; prayſe / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <p>AFter thiſe thre kynges were come wyth gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te traueylle to the hyll of Vaws afore ſayde then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they made there a fayr chapell in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe of the chylde that they had ſought / And they made couenaunt to mete togyder all thre at that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb facs="tcp:10351:23"/>chapell ones in the yere at a certayn daye aſſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned / &amp; there they ordeyned their ſepultures / ¶ Then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a lytyll whyle after all the prynces &amp; the lordes and the worſhipfull knyghtes of theyr londes &amp; kyngdo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes herynge of the comynge home of thyſe thre kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. anone they rode to theym wyth grete ſolempny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and mette wyth theym at the ſayde chapell / And wyth grete mekeneſſe &amp; reuerence they receyued the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ym / And whan the prynces &amp; lordes herde how mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueyllouſly god had wroughte by thyſe thre kynges / thenne they had theim in more reuerence &amp; loue and drede euer after / ¶ So whan thyſe thre kynges had ordeyned theyr Teſtamentes &amp; done what they wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. thenne they toke leue eche of other / And eche of theym wyth his owne people rode hoome vnto hys owne londe wyth grete Ioye &amp; ſolempnyte. and thꝰ eche kynge departed from other in theyr perſones / but neuer in theyr hertes / And whan they were reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their owne londes. thenne they tolde and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to all the people all that they had ſeen and done in theyr waye / And they dyde make in theyr Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples a ſterre after the ſame fourme and likneſſe as it apperyd to theim / Wherfore the Paynems lefte their errours and theyr mawmettes and worſhypped the chylde whyche the kynges had ſoughte / ¶ And thus thiſe thre kynges dwelled in their londes and kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doms in worſhypfull and honeſte conuerſacyon tyll after the Aſcenco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of our lorde Iheſu Cryſte / And
<pb facs="tcp:10351:23"/>wythin ſhorte tyme after thenne came ſaynt Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas thappoſtle in to theyr countrees / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <p>AFter the tyme that thiſe thre kynges were to me from Bedleem in to their owne countre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es agayn / Thenne beganne to ryſe &amp; ſpryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge a grete fame of our lady and of her childe and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre kinges abuote all the countree of Iheruſalem Wherfore our lady for drede of the Iewes fledde ou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of that lytyll houſe that god was borne in &amp; yede in to a nother derke caue vnder the erthe / And there ſhe abode wyth her chylde to the tyme of her Purifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cacyon / And as goddys wyll was dyuers men &amp; wy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men louyd our lady ſaynt Mary and her ſone. and founde theym all manere neceſſaryes that theim ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded / ¶ And after whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth began to wexe and encreaſe. thenne was edifyed there a chapell in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me caue in worſhyppe of the thre kynges and of ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynt Nicholas / ¶ And in that chapell there is a ſtone whyche our lady was wont to ſytte on whan ſhe ya<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue her chylde our lorde Iheſu Cryſte ſucke / And on a tyme as ſhe ſatte vppon that ſtone in gyuynge to her ſwete chylde ſucke. there hapned to falle dow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne from her teete a lytyll droppe of that mooſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and mooſt clene vyrgynall mylke on the forſay yd ſtone. the whyche mooſt precyous and pureſt myl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke that fell from that bleſſyd vyrgyn is remaynyng and ſeen there vnto this daye / And the more it is
<pb facs="tcp:10351:24"/>ſhrapyd wyth knyues. the more wexyth the mylke / And it is borne in to many dyuers places by pylgry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes ¶ Alſo whan our lady was goon out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lytyll hous in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caue ſhe had forgote her ſmocke behyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de her in the haye of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maynger there our lady laye in / And ſoo bothe haye &amp; ſmocke were hoole &amp; treſſh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſame place vnto the tyme that ſaynt Eleyn y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holy quene that was moder to kyng Conſtantyn ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me to the place / For the Iewes of malyce &amp; of enuye helde that place that Criſte was borne in a foule cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyd place / In ſomoche-that they wold ſuffre no man nor woman ne chylde ne beeſt goo in to that place / ¶ Ferdermore whan our lady had offred vp her chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de in to the temple wyth the turtles &amp; douues after Moyſes lawe. as holy wrytte telleth / And Symeon toke him in his armes &amp; ſayd) Nunc dimittis ſeruu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e &amp;c̈) that is to ſaye / Now lorde lete thy ſecua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>unt be in peas after thy worde / The ſame tyme Sy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meon &amp; Anne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy woman in preſence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes &amp; Phariſees prophecied many thinges of our lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de Iheſu Cryſte as holy wrytte tellyth / And ſo gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te a name was ſpronge of our lady &amp; of her ſone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the Iewes that ſhe myghte not ne durſt not noo lenger abide in that place for drede of Herode &amp; of the Iewes / And the Goſpell ſayth (Angelus dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i apparuit in ſompnis ioſeph dicens Surge &amp; accipe pueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c̈ that is for to ſaye / An angell of god appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryd to Ioſeph in his ſlepe &amp; ſayd Ryſe and take the
<pb facs="tcp:10351:24"/>chylde and his moder and fle in to Egypte. and be there tyll I tell the / For Herode ſhall ſeke the chylde to dyſtroye hym / Thenne Ioſeph roos &amp; toke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and his moder &amp; yede in to Egypte by night and dwelled there tyll Herode was deed / Our lady &amp; her ſone were in Egypte dwellynge .vij. yeres. and it is from Bedleem .xij. dayes Iourney / And in this way as our lady went in to Egypte ſhe ſawe growe drie roſes. the whyche ben callyd the roſes of Ierico. and they growe in noo place of all the countree but on<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in the ſame way / And thiſe roſes the ſhepeherdes of the ſame countree done gadre in tyme of yere &amp; ſell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theym to pylgrymes for bredde &amp; to other men of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> countrees abowte. and ſoo they ben-borne in to dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers londes / ¶ And in the ſame place there our lady dwellyd with her ſone in Egypte is now a gardyne therin growyth bawme. and it is allong &amp; brode as a man maye caſte ſtone / And in that gardyne ben vij. welles in whom our lady wyſſhe her ſone &amp; ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed hym. and waſſhyd her clothes &amp; her ſones clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes / And in that gardine ben many buſſhes of baw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me.&amp; they ben lyke buſſhes of coſes. and ben but ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll hygher than a fadom. and the leues ben lyke to Trayfoylles / And to euery buſſhe a cryſten man o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of the Soudans pryſoners is aſſigned to kepe it &amp; to make it clene / And there is a grete wonder &amp; a merueylous of thiſe buſſhes. for there maye no man kepe theim ne dreſſe theim but he be a cryſten man
<pb facs="tcp:10351:25"/>and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath oft tymes be proued / For whan a Iewe or Paynem kepyth them anone they wexe drye &amp; gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we nomore / And in the moneth of Marche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan is alwaye abydynge in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gardyne / And thenne the roddes of the buſſhes ben kytte like a vyne. and thenne they ben bounde aboute wyth coton. and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the kyttynge of the roddes &amp; the coton ben ſette dyſſhes of ſyluer.&amp; ſo the bawme renneth downe in to the veſſelles thrugh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coton as water renneth out of a vyne / &amp; out of thiſe dyſſhes this bawme is put into a grete potte of ſyluer.&amp; that potte is more than vi. galons / And the Soudan taketh all this bawme in to his owne kepyng ſpecyally. but whan ony meſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſager is ſent from a kynge for bawme. the Soudan yeuyth hym a lytyll vyall full / And whan this baw me is all gadred &amp; dropped out of the roddes. then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e euery cryſten man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath a buſſhe to kepe takith the roddes that ben lefte &amp; ſette theim in water in a cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne potte.&amp; the bawme ſwy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth aboue as it were fat neſſe of fleſſhe / And this bawme is gadred &amp; is good for all manere of broſynge / And yf a man be woun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded it woll make hym hole anone / And this bawme is ſolde to pylgrymes of dyuers countrees / And ſoo it is borne thorugh dyuers londes abowte / But this bame is noo thyng ſoo vertuous ne ſoo good as the bawme that droppyth out of the redes / For that can not be bought of the Soudan by no manere of wyſe For and a man take a droppe of that bawme and
<pb facs="tcp:10351:25"/>laye it on a mannys honde anone it renneth &amp; thyr leth thorugh on that other ſyde. and that place ſhall neuer corrupte ne rote after / And that is called rawe bawme. of whiche bawme it were ouer longe a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere to tell the vertue therof / But all the people in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eeſt bileue that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place is ſuche a vertue of growyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of bawme by cauſe our lady dwelled there .vij. ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res and waſſhed there her clothes and her ſones and alſo bathed hym in thoſe welles as it is aforſayd / </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>FErthermore as it is aforſayd. that Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or kynge of Nubie and of Arabie offryd to god an appyll of golde and .xxx. pence gylte ¶ Of thyſe .xxx. pence ye maye here the begynnyng and the laſt ende / ¶ Thara that was fader to Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham dyde make thyſe .xxx. gylte pence in the name of the kynge of Meſopotania. whyche kynge was called Nylus / And ſo by proceſſe of tyme. this Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham whan he ſholde take his Iourney to goo on pil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gremage oute of the londe and countree of Caldee in to the countree whyche was called Ebron why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che atte that tyme hyghte Arabie. he toke thiſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd .xxx. pence that his fader Thara had doo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke wyth hym / And for thoſe .xxx. pence gylte he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaced and boughte thenne a place for his ſepulture &amp; for his two ſones Iſaac and Iacob / Afterwarde by proceſſe of tyme Ioſeph was ſolde of his bredern in to Egypte by marchauntes of Iſmalie for thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:10351:26"/>ſame .xxx. pence ſente in to the londe of Saba for di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers ſpyces &amp; oynementes for the ſepulture of Iacob &amp; ſo they were put in to the-kynges treſory / Thenne by proceſſe of tyme in kynge Salomons tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> que ne of Saba offred thiſe .xxx. pence wyth many other ryche Iewelles in the temple of god in Iheruſalem / ¶ Soo afterwarde in the tyme of Roboam kynge Salomons ſone whan Iheruſalem was diſtroyed &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple of god ſpoylled. thenne thiſe .xxx. pence gyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te were broughte to the kynge of Arabie &amp; were put in to his treſorye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many other ryche ornamentes that were brought out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple of god / ¶ Then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e afterwarde whan Cryſte was borne. thenne Melchi or kynge of Nubie &amp; Arabie toke thiſe .xxx. pence w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym and many other ryche Iewelles. by cauſe they were of the beſte &amp; fyneſte golde that he had in hys treſory / Therfore he toke thoſe wyth hym &amp; offryd them to god in Bedleem whan he was born / Then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after whan our lady ſaynt Mary yede out of Bedle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em in to Egypte for drede of-kynge Herode.ſhe left thoſe yeftes that were offred to her ſone as ſhe went by the waye knytte all togyder in a clothe / It hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyd after that a ſhepeherde that kepte ſhepe in the ſame countree. the whyche had ſoo grete Infyrmyte &amp; dyſeſe that noo leche myghte heele hym / And alle the good y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had he gaue to dyuers leches to make him hole. but if wolde not be / And as he yede w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſhepe in that felde he founde thoſe .xxx. pence wyth
<pb facs="tcp:10351:26"/>enſence and myrre in a clothe togyd<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:aber"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>er</ex>
                     </expan> / And thoſe gyf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes he kept to hymſelf preuely. tyll a lytyll afore the tyme that Cryſte went to his paſſion / And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhepeherd herde ſpeke of ſuche an holy prophete that heelyd all men of theyr. Infirmytees wyth a worde Thenne-he cam<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to god &amp; prayed hym of grace and of helpe.&amp; thenne our lorde Iheſu Cryſte heeled him anone at a worde. and enfourmed hym in the fayth Thenne the ſhepeherde offred to god wyth good de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uocyon the .xxx. pence wyth enſence.&amp; myrre. as they were bothe all togider in the clothe / And god knewe thoſe gyftes well ynough / And god badde the ſhepe herde goo in to the temple &amp; offre all thyſe thynges on the awter.&amp; ſoo he dyde goddys byddynge &amp; of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred them vp to the awter wyth grete deuoco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n / And whan the preeſt of the temple that kepte the offryng ſawe ſuche an oblaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n offred on the awter. in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyppe therof he reueſt him &amp; encenſed the awter by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe ſuche oblaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns were but ſelden ſeen in that te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. he toke with grete reuerence the ryche offrynges &amp; put theym in to the comyn treſory / ¶ And a lytyll whyle after. that is to ſaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyrde daye tofore Cry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtis paſſyon Iudas Scarioth came in to the temple to the prynces of the lawe &amp; to the Iewes &amp; made co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenaunt with theym to betraye his mayſter god al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty / And for his labour the pryncis of the lawe and the Iewes toke out of the treſory thoſe .xxx. pen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce / ¶ Thenne whan this was done &amp; Cryſte was
<pb facs="tcp:10351:27"/>bytrayed thrugh his diſcyple and ſholde be deed for all mankynde as his ſwete wyll was / Thenne Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das repented him. and yede in to the temple ayen to the prynces of the Iewes &amp; caſte downe ayen to the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ym thyſe .xxx. pence / And thenne as the goſpel ſayth he went &amp; hynge hymſelf / Thenne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes bought wyth xv. of thoſe pence a felde for the ſepultures of pylgrymes as the goſpell tellyth / And the other .xv. pence the Iewes gaaf to the knyghtes that kept the ſepulcre of Cryſte / ¶ Ye ſhall vnderſtonde that the lykneſſe of thiſe .xxx. pence was vſed in all the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree. bothe in name &amp; in moneye from Abrahams ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me vnto the dyſtrucco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of Iheruſalem. the whyche was by Titus &amp; Daſpaſianus dayes diſtroyed / But from the tyme of Abraham vnto the tyme of Cryſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tys paſſion thiſe .xxx. pence were neuer dyſceuered ne departed but euermore were bore hole togyder / And whan Cryſte was ſolde for theym. anone they were departed &amp; ſparpled aboute in dyuers places / ¶ And the cauſe why thyſe .xxx. Pence were callyd ſyluer in the goſpell. not wythſtondyng they were fyne golde / For it is the comyn vſage in all the countree ſoo for to calle theym / As men calle of this countree golde of beyonde the ſee. as Scutes. motenes. or florens / And yet in the Eeſt the ſame prynte is made bothe in golde &amp; ſyluer and copre. and is kept amonge gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te lordes of that countree / And the prynte of thyſe pence is on the one ſide a kynges heed crowned. and
<pb facs="tcp:10351:27"/>on that other ſyde it is wreten wyth lettres of Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee. the whyche wrytynge men can not redde now / And one of theym is worche .x. ſhelynges. or better than thre floreyns / And many moo merueylies ben tolde of thyſe thyrty pence. of whom it were a longe proceſſe to telle / ¶ Alſo whan our lady and Ioſeph were warned to come out of Egypt bi an angel as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell tellyth / Thenne they were bydden to goo in to Galilee. and there they dwelled in a cyte whiche was called Nazareth / And ſo the prophecye was ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fylled (Quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nazarenus vocabitur) that is to ſay He ſhall be called a man of Nazareth / ¶ And what Cryſte dyde werke in erthe from that tyme tyll the thyrde yere afore his paſſion. the Euangeliſtes open<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly declare not in theyr goſpelles / </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <p>WHan our lorde Iheſu Criſte was ſtyed vp in to heuen. after that he ſente ſaynt Thomas thapoſtle in to Ynde to preche there goddys worde / In whiche Ynde as it is aforſayd thiſe thre kynges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme regnyd &amp; were lordes of thoſe londes And though it ſoo were that ſaynt Thomas ayenſt his will yede in to the londes of Ynde. yet it was do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of grete prouydence of god. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame appoſtle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> put his honde in to goddys ſyde to knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he was very god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was ryſen fo deth to lyfe for ſaluaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of man ſhold go &amp; preche the Paſſion of Cryſt. his Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſurrecco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n.&amp; his Aſcenco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n to thoſe worſhypful kinges
<pb facs="tcp:10351:28"/>that ſought our lorde in Bedleem in his byrth. and there wyth yeftes worſhypped him / ¶ And as ſaynt Gregory ſayth) Quod omnibus nobis ꝓfuit ꝙ hij tres reges eiuſdem dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i noſtri <abbr>ih<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>u</abbr> 
                  <abbr>xp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i</abbr> infanciam que ſierunt et oculis viderunt et deuotiſſime muneribus adorauerunt &amp; probauerunt) that is to ſaye / It was prouffyte to vs all that thyſe worſhypfull kynges &amp; theyr people ſoughte the childhede of Cryſte. &amp; with theyr eyen dyde ſe hym. and wyth theyr gyftes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhypfully &amp; deuoutly honoured hym and ſothly pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyd it / ¶ Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaynt Barthylmew. Symon &amp; Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that were Criſtis appoſtles were ſente in to Ynde to preche the faythe amonge all the people / For there ben many partyes of Ynde / And one parte of Ynde is more than all the partie of the worlde on this hal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe of the ſee / For this partye of Criſtendom on this halfe the ſee is no more acounted in all theeſt but an hundred dayes Iourney / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <p>AFter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaynt Thomas thappoſtle had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chid in the kingdom of Ynde goddis worde &amp; had goon abowte all the Yndes &amp; the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynces &amp; done many myracles thorugh the ſygne &amp; token of the Croſſe &amp; of goddis worde / As he yede a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boute in the temples he founde a ſterre paynted in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery temple after the ſterre y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> apperyd to the .iij. kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges whan Cryſte was borne. in whiche ſterre was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne of a croſſe &amp; a chylde aboue / And whan ſaynt
<pb facs="tcp:10351:28"/>Thomas ſawe the ſterre he aſked of byſſhops of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple what is was / And biſſhops tolde ſaynt Tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas how ſuche a ſterre apperyd of olde tyme vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyll of Vaws in tokenynge of a chylde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was borne &amp; ſholde be kynge of Iewes. as it was herde out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſterre / And for that cauſe thyſe thre kynges ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de out of theyr londes in to Bedleem worſhypfully thrugh ledynge of the ſterre &amp; came in to Bedleem in .xiij. dayes. and there offred to the childe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. but with grete traueyle afterwarde they came ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me in to theyr owne londes in two yere / And as tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe thre kynges hadd done &amp; ſeen the byſſhops of the temple tolde to ſaynt Thomas thapoſtle / Whan ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynt Thomas herde all this he thanked god.&amp; with grete Ioye he preched to the byſſhops &amp; to all the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the chyldhede of god. his paſſion. his reſurrecco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n &amp; his aſcencyon. and all the werkis of Cryſte whyle he was in erthe / Where thorugh the byſſhops of the temples &amp; many other folke were conuerted to Cryſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te &amp; were cryſtned / Ferthermore ſaynt Thomas me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kely declared and dyde expowne to al the people the vnderſtondyng of this ſterre &amp; of the Croſſe / And he caſted out of the Temples all mawmettes / And he halowed theym in the name &amp; in the worſhyppe of that chylde Cryſte Iheſu / And thenne ſuche a fame beganne to riſe in all that countree abowte of ſaynt Thomas for the grete myracles that he wroughte. that all folke that hadde Infyrmytees or ony other
<pb facs="tcp:10351:29"/>tormentynge of wyckyd ſpyrytes they came to ſaynt Thomas / And he in the name of god and by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of the Croſſe heelyd theym. and conuerted theym to Cryſtis fayth. and cryſtned theym. and they that were ſoo conuerted to Cryſte dyde many myracles thorugh the vertue &amp; ſygne of the Croſſe afterward in dyuers places there as ſaynt Thomas hadde not vyſited ne ben / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <p>SO whan ſaynt Thomas had thus preched and taughte the people / Thenne he yede to the kyngdoms of thoſe thre kynges &amp; foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de them hole of body and of grete aege / And as Sy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meon had anſwere of the holy ghoſt. that he ſholde not deye tyll he had ſeen Cryſte goddis ſone. and ſo he abode him tyll he was broughte in to the temple and there he toke hym in his armes / So in lyke wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe thyſe thre kynges prayed to god that they ſholde not deye tyll they were renewed wyth the holy ghoſt &amp; wyth the ſacrament of Baptym / Soo whan they herde that a man that was diſciple of Cryſt was co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me in to theyr londes that was callyd Thomas. &amp; prechyd to the people of the chyldhode of Cryſt and of his Paſſyon. Reſurrecco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n. and Aſcencyon. and of thoſe werkes that Cryſte dyde here in erthe. and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyally of the ſacrament af baptym / Anone notwyth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtondyng that they were of grete aege and feble. yet they arayed them and came al thre kynges to ſaynt
<pb facs="tcp:10351:29"/>Thomas wyth other lordes and grete multitude of people / And ſaynt Thomas wyth grete Ioye and reuerence receyued theym. and declaryd to theym all that Cryſt taught here in erthe to his dyſcyples. and alſo his paſſyon / And how he roos from dethe to ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe the thirde daye. and alſo how he ſtyed vp to heuen And how he ſente downe the holy ghoſt to the apoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tles. and many other artycles of the fayth / And ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally he tolde theym of the ſacrament of Baptym wythout whyche ſacrament there maye noo man co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me-to the kyngdom of heuen / And whan they were thus enfourmyd and Inſtructe in the fayth. thenne ſaynt Thomas cryſtnyd theym and more ouer all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people that came wyth theym / And anone thiſe thre kynges were replete and fulfylled of the holy ghoſt / And began co preche wyth ſaynt Thomas goddys worde / And alſo they tolde the people how they had ſoughte Cryſte goddys ſone in Bedleem in his Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiuyte as it is tolde before / So whan all this was do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne thyſe thre kynges wente wyth ſaynt Thomas &amp; all theyr people to the hylle of Vaws / And there ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynt Thomas dyde halowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chapell that thoſe thre kynges had done made and edifyed vpon that hyll And there ſaynt Thomas &amp; thoſe thre kynges pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched agayne to all the people of Criſten byleue. and of the ſterre that apppered to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre kyngis / And ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che a Ioye and gladneſſe was amonge the people. and ſuche a name was ryſen in al the londes aboute
<pb facs="tcp:10351:30"/>of ſaynt Thomas and of thiſe thre kynges criſtned that all manere of people bothe men and wymmen came from dyuerſe and ferre countrees wyth greate deuocyon to viſyte that chapell that was made on the hyll of Vaws / And for that grete concours and deuoco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n that was made to the chapell. thoſe thre kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges dyde make vnder that hylle a grete and a ryche cyte / And is called the cyte of Seuyll / And that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rycheſt and the beſte cyte of all Ynde / And yet vnto this daye in that cyte is the habytacyon of Prethyr Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n that is lorde of Ynde / And there dwellyth al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo the Patryarke of Ynde. that is called Patryarke Thomas / ¶ And why the Patriarke of Ynde is cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyd Thomas. and why the lorde of Ynde is called Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n ye ſhall here afterwarde / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <p>WHanne ſaynt Thomas the appoſtle hadde preched and conuertyd the people to the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of our Sauyour Cryſte Iheſu. thenne he ſacred and made thyſe thre kynges vnto thordre of preeſthode and afterwarde vnto Archebyſſhops / And whan they were put in this degree. thenne they ordeyned vnder theim biſſhops. preeſtes and clerkes to ſerue god / And thenne thyſe forſayde thre kynges and byſſhops halowed all the Temples in that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree in-worſhippe &amp; honour of our lady. and caſted out all the mawmettes that were in the temples in that countree aboute / And to biſſhops &amp; preeſtes and
<pb facs="tcp:10351:30"/>Thiſe thre kynges and Archebyſſhops gaaf many grete poſſeſſions to mayntene &amp; encreaſe goddis ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſe / Alſo ſaynt Thomas taughte thiſe kynges &amp; Archebyſſhops &amp; other byſſhops and preeſtes the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nere &amp; the fourme to ſaye a maſſe. and enfourmyd theim alſo of the wordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Cryſte ſayd to his diſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. whan he made his ſupper y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nyght that he was betrayed. thrugh whiche wordes he made &amp; ordeyned the Sacrament of the awter / And alſo he taughte theym the Pater noſter &amp; many other thynges he tolde theim / Alſo the fourme of cryſtnynge &amp; ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally charged theim that they ſholde not forgete that And whan ſaynt Thomas had enfourmyd theym thus of the Cryſten fayth. thenne afterwarde he to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke martyrdom for the lawe of Cryſte. as it is contey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned more fully in the ſtory that is wreten of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion / There it tellyth how he was ſlayne &amp; in what place / But ſothly in all that countree abowte there ſaynt Thomas was ſlayn bothe men &amp; wy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue vyſages ſhapen after houndes. but they ben not heery. and ſoo they ben yet vnto this daye / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <p>AFter the dethe of ſaynt Thomas thyſe thre kynges Archebiſſhops yede abowte citees &amp; townes &amp; other dyuers places and ordeyned many chyrches and putte in theim byſſhops preeſtes &amp; clerkes &amp; other mynyſters of holy chyrche to do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ſeruyte / And moche rycheſſe &amp; grete poſſeſſyons
<pb facs="tcp:10351:31"/>And thenne the thre kynges Arch<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>biſſhops forſoke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vanyte of the worlde. and ordeyned theym to abyde in the cyte of Seuyll. the whyche they had doo buyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / And they aſſygned certayne lordes to gouerne &amp; rule theyr kyngdoms &amp; londes bothe in ſpyritualtie &amp; temporalte / And all people of grete loue &amp; charyte were obedyent to theim. as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſone to the fad<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> / Then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the ſeconde yere tofore theyr dethe thyſe thre kynges &amp; Archebyſſhops made a Conuocaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of all the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple bothe ſpyrytuall and temporall / And had theym all to a certayne place / And they warnyd &amp; counſey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the people that they ſholde be perſeueraunt in the cryſten fayth as ſaynt Thomas had taught theim And counſeyled the people that they ſholde be all of one acorde and of one wyll to choſe a man amonge theim that were able and diſcrete that had loue and deſyre to mayntene the fayth of Cryſtendom. And that man ſholde be cheyf tofore alle other men. as in ſpirytualte in ſaynt Thomas ſtede / And to hym all manere of men ſhall obeye as to theyr ghoſtly fader Whiche man in worſhyp of ſaynt Thomas thapoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle ſholde be called the Patriarke Thomas for euer laſtyng memory / And whan the Patriarke were de de thenne they ſholde come togyder all in one place &amp; in his ſtede cheſe another. to whom as it is aforſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yd they ſholde obeye as to theyr ghoſtly fad<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> / Then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e whan this matere was thus-ſpoke amonge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple they aſſented therto. And of one accorde &amp; wyll
<pb facs="tcp:10351:31"/>they choſe a man that was called Iacob. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyche was come out of the countree of Anchioche. and he had alway folowed ſaynt Thomas the appoſtle in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Ynde / And this Iacob the people choſe and toke hym for theyr Patriarke / And chaunged his name and callyd hym Thomas / And this man Iacob was the firſte Patriarke that was in that countree / And ſoo alwaye they of Ynde be obedient to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryarke Thomas as we ben to the Pope of Rome yet vnto thyſe dayes / And to this Patriarke and ſo al his ſucceſſours thyſe thre kinges gaaf for euermo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re wych the aſſente of alle the people the Tythes of all theyr londes and kyngdoms / Whan all this was done and the Patryarke Thomas thenne choſen to be lorde of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people in ſpirytualte / Thenne thiſe iij. kinges Archebyſſhops &amp; other biſſhops of comin aſſente of all the people choſe a nother man y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was diſcrete to be lorde &amp; gouernour of al the people in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poralte / And for this cauſe. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf ony man wolde ryſe or tempte ayenſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Patriarke Thomas or ayenſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of god. yf ſo were y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Patriarke might not ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le him by the ſpirytuall lawe. then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold this lord of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall lawe chaſtiſe him by his power / So this lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſholde not be called a kynge or emperour. but he ſholde be callyd Prethir Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n / And the cauſe is this For the thre kynges were preeſtes and of theyr poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſyons they made hym lorde / For there is noo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree ſo highe as preſthode is in all the worlde. nor ſo
<pb facs="tcp:10351:32"/>worthy / Alſo he is callyd Prethyr Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n in worſhyp<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſaynt Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n the Euangelyſte that was a preeſt. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt ſpecyall choſen and loued of god almyghty / ¶ Whan all this was done thyſe thre kynges aſſyg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned the Patriarke Thomas &amp; Prethyr Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n thone to be cheyf gouernour in ſpyrytualtie. and the other cheyf lorde in temporalte for euer more / And ſoo thi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ſame lordes &amp; gouernours of Ynde ben called vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thyſe dayes / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <p>WHan all thynge was thus dyſpoſed &amp; ordey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned by thiſe .iij. worthy kinges. thenne they went in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyte of Seuyll forſayd. and the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re they lyued two yeres / And a lytyll tofore the feeſt of the Natyuyte of our lorde Iheſu Cryſte there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peryd a wonderfull ſterre aboue the cyte / By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſterre they vnderſtode that theyr tyme was nyhe that thei ſholde deye &amp; paſſe out of this worlde vnto euerlaſtynge Ioye in heuen / Thenne of one aſſente they ordeyned a large &amp; a fayr tombe for theyr ſepul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture in the ſame chyrche that they had doo make in that cyte / And in the feeſt of Cryſtmas thiſe kinges &amp; Archebyſſhops dyde ſolempnely goddys ſeruyſe. ſo in the feeſt of the Circumſico<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n. Melchior kynge of Arabie &amp; of Nubie ſayd his maſſe ſolemply in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che / And whan he had ſayd maſſe tofore all the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple he layed hym downe. and wythout ony dyſeſe or heuyneſſe he yelde vp his ſpiryte to the fad<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> of heuen
<pb facs="tcp:10351:32"/>And ſoo deyed in the yere of his aege. c. and .xvi.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>THenne came thoſe two other kynges &amp; toke vp his body &amp; arayed it in byſſhops clothes and wyth kynges ornamentes &amp; bare hym to his tombe / And thenne in the feeſt of the Epipha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye Bathazar king of Godolie &amp; of Saba ſayd de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoutly his maſſe &amp; whan he had done. wythout gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uaunce of dyſeſe or ſykneſſe. as the wyll of god was he deyed &amp; paſſed to god in the yere of his aege. c. &amp; xvi. Thenne Iaſper the thyrde kyng toke vp his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy &amp; arayed it as the fyrſte Kynges body was. and wyth grete ſolempnyte layed &amp; buryed it in the tom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be by Melchiors body / The ſixte daye after this Iaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per kynge of Taars &amp; of thyle of Egriſwill. whan he alſo wyth ſolempnyte &amp; grete deuocyon ſayd his maſſe. thenne Cryſte toke his ſpiryte to hym &amp; to his blyſſe / And thenne came other Byſſhops &amp; preeſtes with moche people &amp; toke his body &amp; arayed it wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thyly as the other kynges bodyes were. &amp; bare it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tombe there thother kinges laye. And Cryſt ſhewed there this wonder tofore all the people / ¶ Whan the body of the thirde kynge was thenne broughte and ſholde be buryed &amp; layed in the ſame tombe bytwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the other kinges. anone eche of the other two kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges departed aſonder &amp; yaue place to theyr thyrde fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe. &amp; ſo receyued hym to lye in the mydyll betwix theim both / And ſo it may be ſayd of thiſe thre kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:10351:33"/>as it is radde in holy wrytte (<abbr>Glioſi</abbr> principes terre qm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o in vita ſua dilexerunt ſe iſa &amp; in morte non ſunt ſeperati &amp;c̈) that is to ſay / As thiſe gloryous kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges &amp; Archebiſſhops loued togyd<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:aber"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>er</ex>
                     </expan> in theyr lyfe. right lo they ben not departed in theyr dethe / And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſterre that apperyd ouer the cyte tofore theyr dethe abode alwaye ſtyll tyll theyr bodyes were tranſlated vnto Colayne as men of Ynde ſaye / </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <p>LOnge after the dethe of thyſe thre kynges. whan Cryſten faythe ſtode in proſperyte in the worſhypfull cyte of Seuyll &amp; in alle the kyngdoms of the Eeſt. thenne the deuyll that of all goodnes &amp; vertues is dyſtroyer thrugh his wyckyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. excyted &amp; broughte vp amonge the people dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers oppynyons of hereſie / And the perſecuco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of he reſye gretly encreaſed in dyuers londes abowte. &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo in the cyte of Ceuyll that thyſe thre kynges reſted in. In ſo moche that Prethir Iohn and Patriarke Thomas myghte not rebuke the people from theyr hereſies by noo ſpirytuall correccyon nor temporall. And ſoo the people tornyd agayne to theyr olde lawe and wretchyd fals mawmettes &amp; fals goddys / And forſoke the lawes of god in ſomoche that thyſe thre kynges bodies were had at noo reuerence. but almoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te forgoten of the people / And ſoo the people that en habyted in the cyte of Seuyll that were come out of the londes &amp; kyngdoms of thyſe thre kynges. euery
<pb facs="tcp:10351:33"/>party toke his kynges bodi out of the tombe. and clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed theim in dyuers cheſtes honeſtly. eche by hymſelf and bare them home in to theyr owne londes &amp; kyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gedoms / And wyth grete worſhyp euery londe vecey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the body of theyr kynge. and there they abode longe tyme after / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <p>Whan this gloryous Emperour Conſtantyn thorugh the grace of god &amp; dyuers myracles was conuerted to Cryſte by ſaynt Silueſter and he was made clene of his leprehede &amp; was chaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged both in lyfe &amp; in maners in to a newe man. that is to ſaye in to the lawe of Cryſte / And the ſame ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me ſaynt Elyne whiche was moder of Conſtantyn the emperour aforſayd was dwellynge amonge the Iewes / And ſhe was al enfecte &amp; defoylled wyth the Iewes lawes and with theyr byleue / But wond<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhe was conuerted to the lawes of Cryſte. as it is wreten in the ſtory of her lyffe &amp; of the fyndynge of the holy Croſſe it is more playnly ſhewed / And fro thenſforth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bleſſyd ſaynt Elyne of as mighty ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yngth as ſhe was fyrſt in the Iewes lawe occupieng &amp; drawyng to it.ſomoche more beſily ſhe brenned af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terwarde in the newe lawe and goſpel of Cryſt Ihe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu / And al the holy places y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lorde halowed there &amp; in other parties <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his manhede as ſhe had defoyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led by counſeyle of the Iewes. ſhe afterwarde to the laude of our lorde I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſu deuoutly viſyted. honoured
<pb facs="tcp:10351:34"/>and enlarged rychely wyth grete yefces to the confu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of the Iewes / Wherfore afterwarde by myracle whan ſaynt Eleyne had founde the croſſe &amp; naylles by the wyll of our lorde Iheſu. thenne vpon y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame place &amp; vpon the mount of Caluarie &amp; vpon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulture of Cryſte. and the place y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Cryſte apperyd to Mary Mawdeleyne in lykneſſe of a gardyner. alle thiſe places &amp; many other y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were holy the quene ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynt Eleyne buylded chyrches on / And made ryall &amp; worſhypfull chyrches aboue alle thoſe places.&amp; alſo ſhe yede in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place where thangell apperyd to our la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy. &amp; there thangell apperyd to the ſhepeherdes that nyght y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god was borne / And in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame ſhe dyde bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ylde a ryall chyrche &amp; namyd it (<abbr>Glia</abbr> in excelſis (&amp; ſo it is callyd vnto this daye / And this chirche was ſomtyme a grete Colage of Chanons. whiche of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyall preuilege began al the Houres of the day with <abbr>Glia</abbr> in excelſis (as we doo in this countree w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (De<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us in adiutoriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (&amp; ſome men vſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame yet this day in the ſame chyrche / Whan ſaynt Elyne had made the chirche. thenne ſhe went in to Bedleem in to the ſame place where Cryſte was borne / And as it is tol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de before the Iewes of enuye wolde ſuffre noo man chylde ne beeſt to goo in to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place. for they helde it a curſyd place / And fro y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lady ſaynt Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry was goon out of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place that ſhe bare in her chyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de tyll ſaynt Elyne came in to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place. came neuer man chylde ne beeſt / And whan ſaynt Elyne came
<pb facs="tcp:10351:34"/>in to that derke place. ſhe fonde the ſame haye that Cryſte was layed in &amp; the maynger and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> clothes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our lorde Iheſu was wrapped in.&amp; our ladies ſmoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / All thiſe thynges our lady had lefte behynde her whan ſhe yede out of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place in to Egypte. whyche ſaynt Elyne founde bothe fayr &amp; hoole wounde to gyder in the maynger / </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>ALl thyſe thynges that be relykes ſaynt Ely<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne toke awaye wyth her.ſauf the maynger. &amp; bare them in to Conſtantynople / And the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re wyth grete reuerence &amp; ſolempnyte ſhe put theym in to a worſhypful chirche. that is called the chyrche of ſaynt Sophie / And therin the relykes were kepte vnto the tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a kynge of Fraunce that hight Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolus came vnto Iheruſalem. and there dyde many grete bataylles ayenſt the Sarraſins / And delyured out of pryſon all the cryſten men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> longe tyme had liued there / &amp; whan he had done. he yede home ayen by Conſtantynople.&amp; he ſawe al thyſe relykes / And wyth grete prayer he had all thyſe relykes. and bare theym home wyth hym in to Fraunce.&amp; putt theym in a worſhypful chyrche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is callyd our lady chyrche of Akon / And there is our ladyes ſmocke &amp; other re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lykes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben worſhypped of Cryſten men there vnto this day / ¶ Whan ſaynt Elyne had made thiſe chyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches. thenne ſhe went in to the cite of Nazareth. and there ſhe made alſo a fayr chyrche / And ordeyned to
<pb facs="tcp:10351:35"/>theym byſſhops. preeſtes &amp; clerkes to mayntene ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in dyuyne ſeruyſe / And in the cyte of Nazareth than gell greted our lady.&amp; it is in the londe of Galilee / And beſyde Galilee is an hyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is callyd Thabor / Vpon that hyll our lorde Iheſu Criſte tranſfigured hym tofore thre of his dyſcyples. Peter. Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n.&amp; Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mys. as the goſpell tellyth / And this hyll is but lytyl of brede. but it is wonder hyghe / And it is from Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem thre dayes Iourney &amp; an half / And bitwyx Iheruſalem &amp; this hyll Thabor was all the way y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Cryſt yede here in erthe with his diſcyples &amp; preched &amp; taught and dyde myracles.&amp; ferder yede he not in his manhede than bytwene thiſe two places &amp; other places that were bytwene theym but ryght lytyll of brede and largeneſſe / </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <p>WHan this quene ſaynt Elyne had viſited al thiſe holy places.&amp; had ordeyned chirches &amp; goddis mynyſtres for to ſerue. and all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge perfourmyd after her owne wyll to the worſhyp of god / Thenne began ſhe to thynke gretly on thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe thre kynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had worſhipped god in his chyldhe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / And ſhe arayed her wyth a certayn people &amp; yede in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> londes of Ynde / Whan ſhe was there ſhe dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>troyed all the Synagoges &amp; fals mawmettes. &amp; dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de make chirches &amp; monaſteries / &amp; ordeyned in them preeſtes &amp; clerkes of the cryſten faythe / And ſhe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyd the cryſted fayth amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people. the whyche
<pb facs="tcp:10351:35"/>was taughte by ſaynt Thomas thappoſtle and the thre kynges. whyche fayth thrugh hereſies was dyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>troyed.&amp; ſhe renewyd it thorugh her prechynge / For all the people whan they herde what myracles oure lorde Iheſu Cryſte had wroughte by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worſhypfull quene ſaynt Elyne. of the fynding of the croſſe &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> naylles &amp; of our ladyes ſmocke &amp; of the haye. and of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clothes that Cryſte was wrapped in. in his chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dehode / Thenne they came to her &amp; worſhipped her and forſoke their fals lawe &amp; toke them to the lawe of god as ſaynt Elyne taughte theym / And thenne ſhe began to enquere of the relykes of the thre kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / And wyth grete traueylle yede abowte to haue theym / Soo our lorde Iheſu Cryſte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euermore is re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy to al men that crye to hym in truthe &amp; ryghtwyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / As he ſhewed to this holy quene the croſſe &amp; the naylles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were hydde depe in the erthe. ryght ſoo he ſhewed the bodies of the thre kinges to her / So this lady had ſuche a name amonge the people. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>triarke Thomas &amp; Preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n by counſell of the lordes yaue to ſaynt Elyne the .ij. bodies of thyſe .ij. kynges. Melchior &amp; Balthazar to the worſhippe of god &amp; of the holy kynges / The body of the thyrde kynge Iaſper. the Neſtorynes had borne it in to the yle of Egriſwill / And by cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaynt Elyne wold not that thiſe thre kynges ſhold be departed.ſhe ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de grete meanes &amp; grete prayers. and yaue grete gyf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes to the cheyf lordes of the-yle. and ſo ſhe gate the
<pb facs="tcp:10351:36"/>thyrde body. that is to ſaye of Iaſper / And for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy ſhe gaaf to theym the body of ſaynt Thomas y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> appoſtle whyche ſhe had that tyme in her kepynge. And the body of ſaynt Thomas hath ben twyes bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ren awaye from the yle. &amp; euer reſtored ayen for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayn cauſes / ¶ And cryſten men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue ben in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yle ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myghte neuer ſe the body of ſaynt Tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mas / For it is a comyn prophecye in alle y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countree that the body of ſaynt. Thomas the apoſtle ſhall be tranſlated to the cyte of Coleyne &amp; putte to the thre kynges / And in what manere this ſhall be done thei tell &amp; ſaye / ¶ In tyme comyng whan god wyll the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re ſhall be an archebiſſhop of Coleyne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhall be ſoo wyſe &amp; prudent &amp; ſoo myghty. that he ſhall make a contracte of matrimonye bytwene the emperours ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne of Rome &amp; themperours doughter of Tartarin / And wyth this contracte &amp; frendſhyp the holy londe ſhall be yelden in to criſten mennys hondes / And in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme ſhall the body of ſaynt Thomas be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted &amp; born to Coleyne &amp; layed bi the thre kynges.&amp; therfore the Heretykes of this yle y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben called Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines taken but lytyll hede of ſaynt Thomas body ne doo but lytyll reuerence therto by cauſe of prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye.¶ And thenne ſaynt Elyne put y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodyes of thy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe thre kynges togyder in a cheſte / &amp; arayed it wyth grete rycheſſe &amp; thenne brought it to Conſtantyno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wyth grete Ioye and reuerence / And layed theim reuerently in a chyrche y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was callyd ſaynt Sohpie / 
<pb facs="tcp:10351:36"/>and that ſame chyrche kynge Conſtantyn dyde ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke / And he alone wyth a lytyll chylde ſette vp all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pylars of marbyll of the ſame chyrche / And therin was ſomtyme the crowne of thorne that Cryſt was crowned wyth / And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Turkes &amp; Sarraſyns came downe to Conſtantynople &amp; diſtroyed a grete party therof. thenne themperour ſent to ſaynt Lowes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was thenne kyng of Fraunce for ſocour &amp; helpe.&amp; thenne king Lowes came with ſtrength to the them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour.&amp; recouered ayen the mooſt party of that lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> themperour had loſt / And for his labour them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour gaaf hym the crowne of thorne. wherfore the Grekes made moche ſorowe / And ſo came the holy crowne of thorne in to Fraunce out of Conſtantyno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is the cheif cyte of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> londe of Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce ¶ And whan thiſe thre knges were brought vnto Conſtantynople all the people of the countree abow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te came &amp; viſyted theym &amp; wyth grete deuoco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhypped theym / And there they were longe tyme / </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <p>AFter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thiſe thre worſhipfull kynges bodies were brought vnto Conſtantynople. kynge Conſtantyn &amp; his holy moder ſaynt Elyne deyed / And ayenſt the fayth of cryſten men began to ryſe a newe hereſye.&amp; alſo perſecuco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of dethe ayenſt all thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wolde mayntene the cryſten faythe &amp; the lawe of Cryſte / But in this perſecuco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n the Grekes though it were y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had many worſhipfull docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urs
<pb facs="tcp:10351:37"/>&amp; byſſhops of the ſame countree of Grece borne Yet thei forſoke the lawe of holy chirche &amp; the fayth and choſe theim a Patriarke by themſelf. to whom they obeye yet vnto this daye as we do to the pope / &amp; in this perſecuco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n the bodies of thiſe thre kinges we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re had in noo reuerence. nor none of the other relikes but vtterly ſet at nought / And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sarraſyns &amp; Tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes in this tyme wanne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtronge honde &amp; batayll the londes of Grece &amp; Armonye.&amp; dyſtroyed a gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te parte of thoſe londes / And thenne came thempero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ur of Rome Mauricius.&amp; thrugh him &amp; the helpe of theim of Melayne recoueryd-all thiſe londes agayn ¶ And as it is ſayd amonge theym there in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree. thrugh counſeyle of the ſame emperour thyſe .iij kynges bodies were tranſlate in to Melayne / ¶ Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore it is in many bokes in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> countree. y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there was an emperour of Grece whiche was called Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namiell.&amp; he ſent vnto a relygyous man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd Guſtorgius in to Melayne vpon a certayn meſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſage.&amp; thenne the religious man aſked of thempero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ur to haue thyſe thre kynges bodies / And by cauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperour loued well this man &amp; alſo he was a wyſe man. themperour graunted hym the bodyes of thiſe kyngis / And ſo this man Guſtorgius ſent the body<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es to Melane.&amp; layed theim there in a fayre chirche of frere Prechours wyth grete ſolempnyte / And the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re our lorde ſhewed many fayre myracles / </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>¶ And ſo at yet we ſhal leue to ſpeke of the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n
<pb facs="tcp:10351:37"/>of thiſe holy kynges bodyes &amp; ſpeke of another matere in vſage of the londes of Ynde / </p>
                  <p>PReter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is lorde of Ynde &amp; of alle the kynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben vnder hym on the xij. daye. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is called the Epiphanie. they araye theym as kynges ſholde with their crownes on their hedes &amp; with ryche ornamentes.ſo they go to theyr temple &amp; here maſſe / &amp; thre tymes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> day they offre at maſſe The fyrſte offrynge in the begynnyng of the maſſe the ſeconde after the goſpell.&amp; the thyrde at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comyn of the maſſe / And they offre golde. encenſe.&amp; myrre. and that wyth grete deuoco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n &amp; mekenes. and alſo other lordes of leſſe degree offre thries after the yr power / Ferd<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:aber"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>er</ex>
                     </expan>more all other men of cryſten faythe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben diuyded in dyuers partyes &amp; ſectes. &amp; holde dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers opinyons of hereſies. as Nubiani. Soldani. neſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torini. Indi. Grecy. Simani. Ifymum Nycholaite &amp; Mandopoly. of thiſe eche party hath a deuoco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n to the thre kynges &amp; to the feeſt of the Epyphanie. as ye maye here afterwarde / But fyrſte or we procede ony ferther we ſhall ſpeke of the thre kynges bodies lefte at Melayne / </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <p>THenne after by proceſſe of tyme the cyte of Melane beganne to rebell agaynſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perour theyr ſouereyne lorde. whyche empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was called Fredericus / And this emperour ſent
<pb facs="tcp:10351:38"/>to the biſſhop of Loleyne that was called Reynolde for helpe of dyuers lordes of the londe. for dyuers lor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were his enmyes toke the cyte of Melane &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>troyed a grete parte therof / And in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme the grete men of the cyte toke the bodyes of thyſe thre kynges &amp; hydde them preuely in the erthe / Amonge al other there was a lorde in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cyte that highte Aſſo.&amp; them perour hated this Aſſo more than al the people of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cyte / And ſo it happed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the dyſtrucco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of the cyte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Archebiſſhop of Colayn wan this lordis place tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rugh ſtrong honde.&amp; laye therin a grete whyle / And this Aſſo was take and put in priſon / Thenne this Aſſo ſent preuely by the kepers of the priſon to thar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chebyſſhop of Coleyne &amp; prayed hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me &amp; ſpeke wyth hym / And ſoo whan he was come before tharchebyſſhop he promyſed him yf he mygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te &amp; wolde gete hym grace of themperour &amp; his loue &amp; lordſhyp. he wolde yeue hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bodyes of the thre kynges / And whan the byſſhop herde this anone he yede to themperour &amp; prayed for him. and gate hym grace &amp; good loue of the emperour / Whan this was done this lorde Aſſo brought preuely the bodyes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre kynges to tharchebiſſhop of Colayn / And then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Archebyſſhop ſente preuely thyſe thre bodyes by his preuy meyne a grete waye out of Melayne / And thenne he yede to the Emperour &amp; prayed hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde graunt hym the bodyes of the thre kynges / &amp; themperour graunted theim to him / And thenne the
<pb facs="tcp:10351:38"/>Archebyſſhop openly wyth grete proceſſyon &amp; ſolem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyte brought thiſe holy ſayntes in to Coleyne.&amp; the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re layed theym in a fayr chyrche of ſaynt Peter wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhypfully / And all the people of the countree w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all reuerence y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myght receyued thyſe holy relykes / there they ben worſhypped of all manere of naco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns vnto this daye / </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>And thus endyth the tranſlaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n of thyſe thre kynges. melchior. balthazar.&amp; Iaſper / </trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="excursus_on_heresies">
            <p>NOw to ſpeke of thuſages in Ynde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue begon before aſwell of Cryſten as Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tykes &amp; Syſmatykes. eche of theym both re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligyous &amp; ſeculars faſten on Cryſtmas daye vnto it be nyght / And eche man ſpredyth his table &amp; ſettith on it aſmoche meete &amp; drynke as may ſuffyſe for his lyuynge fro Criſtmas daye tyll the .xij. daye / And ſo of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> that is ſett on the borde they ete &amp; drynke with theyr wyues. chyldern &amp; meyne wyth all Ioye &amp; myr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they can in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme / Alſo they lyghte a candell or a lampe.&amp; that ſhall brenne bothe nyghte &amp; daye fro Cryſtmas nyght vnto the .xij. nyghte beſyde the ſame borde / And in the Vigill of the Epiphanie at nyght euery frende gooth to others hous / &amp; whan he cometh to the door he ſayth (Bona dies) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye Good daye / For yf he ſayd (Bona nox) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye Good nyght. thenne wolde he accuſe him tofore the Iuſtiſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe as he had done to hym a grete treſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paas / And ſo they wake all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nyght &amp; goo fro hous
<pb facs="tcp:10351:39"/>to hous. and ete. drinke &amp; daunce. and bere candelles lyght in theyr hondes. in tokenynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſterre ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peryd whan Cryſte was born &amp; lad thiſe .iij. kynges in thyſe dayes to Bedleem.&amp; there was no nyght in this tyme. but it was all one daye to them / Alſo the xij. day al manere Cryſten of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> countree of what ſec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te euer they ben. come fro ferre countrees w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their biſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhops &amp; preeſtys. wyth other relygyous wyth croſſes of ſyluer &amp; ſenſers.&amp; goon to the water of flom Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan whiche is fro <abbr>Ihrlm</abbr> .v. myles / And whan all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people is come to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> water. then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e euery ſecte ſtondyth togider in a certain place by themſelf / And then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſecte takyth his croſſe &amp; layeth it downe on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde.&amp; redyth a goſpell euery ſecte in his owne ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge (Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> natus eſſet ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in bethleem &amp;c̈ (And whan this goſpell is radde. euery ſecte wyth grete deuoco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n worſhippeth his croſſe &amp; offryth therto as euery man is of power / And this is done in tokenynge &amp; myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre kynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> offred yeftes to almyghty god After this they goon all in proceſſion to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re Cryſte was cryſtned of ſaynt Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n Bapcyſt. and there they rede in latyn the goſpel (In illo te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pore ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nit ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s a galilea ad ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>em vt baptizaret<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ab illo in iordane in iſto loco &amp;c̈) that is to ſaye / On a tyme our lorde came fro Galilee to ſaynt Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n to be cryſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tened of ſaynt Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n in this Iordan in this place / And whan the goſpell is radde. they bleſſe the water and waſſhe theyr croſſe in the water / And ſeke men
<pb facs="tcp:10351:39"/>and blynde men goon in to the water nakyd. and waſſhe theym.&amp; after warde ben heelyd / And whan this is done euery ſecte goon home agayn in to their owne-countree / ¶ And bytwene this Iordan &amp; Ihe / ruſalem is a lytyll wylderneſſe that is called Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſt. and therin dwelled ſaynt Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n Baptiſt. and the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re he prechyd / And there our lorde Iheſu Cryſt came to ſaynt Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n to be cryſtned of hym / And in that ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me deſerte god almyghty faſted .xl. dayes &amp; .xl. nygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / ¶ Alſo byſſhops &amp; other preeſtes of what tonge or ſecte that they ben. euery daye after theyr maſſe they ſaye this goſpell) Cum natus eſſet ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (as we in this countree ſaye (In principio) after our maſſe. But eche ſecte ſayth in his owne tonge &amp; not in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyn.ſauf on the .xij. daye oonly / But it is radde dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly ryght as it was done / For in Iheruſalem it is radde thus) <abbr>Aum</abbr> natus eſſet ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in bethleem in diebus herodis. hic regis ecce magi venerunt ab ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente hic dicentes (And in Bedleem and in al the dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ocecyſe abowte it is radde thus) <abbr>Au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </abbr> natus eſſet ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in diebus herodis hic &amp; Iude regis &amp;c̈ (Alſo other criſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten men by whoos places thyſe thre kynges in theyr goynge out and comynge home agayn paſſyd by / for a ſpecyall deuocyon that they haue to the thre kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges they redde this goſpell after this manere of four me (Cum natus eſſet ihu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in bethleem iude in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus herodis regis ecce magi regis glorioſi cum mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ima feſtinacione &amp; excercitu ab oriente venerunt
<pb facs="tcp:10351:40"/>&amp; per nos tranſierunt (And thus all dyuers ſectes rede this goſpell as it was done amonge theim / ¶ Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sarraſyns y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> byleue on Machomites lawe &amp; Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes haue thiſe thre kynges in ſpecyall reuerence in all temples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countree. they were ſomtyme cryſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned.&amp; forſoke it.&amp; dyſtroyed all the ymages in their temples. &amp; kytte of theyr noſes &amp; dyſfygured theym for diſpyte / But the ymages of the thre kinges they ſuffre alwaye ſtonde ſtyll wythout ony diſpyte / </p>
            <p>FErdermore towchynge the ſectes of Herety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes aforſayd / The fyrſt ſecte is callyd Nubi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ani.&amp; thoſe ben of the kingdom of Araby &amp; Nubie. wherof Melchior was kynge.&amp; thiſe ben criſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten men / And they haue a ſpecyall prerogatyf tofore al other cryſten men. for worſhip of their kyng / And the preeſtes of the countree whan they goo to thaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter haue crownes of gold or ouergylt on theyr heedes And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they doo in tokenynge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the thre kynges w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> crownes on their heedes offred yeftes to god almygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty in Bedleem / &amp; wyth crownes &amp; myters ſynge the yr maſſes / </p>
            <p>There is alſo a nother ſecte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is called Soldini. and they ben of the kingdom of Godolie &amp; Saba there Balthazar was kynge / They were a party corrupte in the fayth.&amp; they toke theyr names of an Herety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was called Solodinis / But thiſe men ben not holde in ſoo grete reuerence as the Nubiani. for they
<pb facs="tcp:10351:40"/>kepe not the fayth ſoo truly as they done / And their preeſtis whan they goo to maſſe they beere golde in theyr hondes to the awter.&amp; the deaken be cryth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence &amp; the ſubdeaken myrre / And this they beere in tokenynge of the thre kynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> offred to oure lorde Iheſu Cryſt god almighty in his byrth. golde. myrre &amp; enſence / </p>
            <p>Alſo there is a nother ſecte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is of the kyngdom of Taars &amp; of thyle of Egriſwill there as Iaſper was kynge.&amp; they ben called Neſtorini / And they ben the worſte &amp; the curſedeſt Heretykes of the worlde.&amp; for the mooſt party they ben blacke Ethyopies / And al men of other ſectes hate theim gretly / And whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preeſtis goo to ſynge maſſe. they curſe all men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re of counſeylle. or helpynge to doo awaye the body of Iaſper y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was theyr kynge / ¶ Ferd<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:aber"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>er</ex>
               </expan>more thiſe Neſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torines forſoke Preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n &amp; Thomas theyr Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarke &amp; were rebell ayenſt theym &amp; ayenſt the law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of holy chyrche / Soo afterwarde as the wyll of god was on a tyme there dide aryſe in the ſame lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de a grete multytude of people. as of ſhepeherdes &amp; laborers &amp; bonde men ayenſt theyr owne naco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whyche callyd themſelf Tartarines.&amp; they made a Smythe theyr capytayne &amp; cheyf-lorde / And ſo tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rugh ſtronge power they dyſtroyed al the kyngdom &amp; londes of Neſtorines.&amp; ſlewe all the people wyth out ony mercy as the wyll of god was / And toke caſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>telles. cytees &amp; grete townes &amp; all theyr goodes / And
<pb facs="tcp:10351:41"/>whan the Tartarynes had thus conquered the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des &amp; kyngdoms of the Neſtorines. thenne the Neſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torines yede to Preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n &amp; promyſed hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wolde torne ayen to theyr fyrſt lawe &amp; fayth of god &amp; be trybutory to hym ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he wold helpe them / And then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e Preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n was in good wyll to helpe theim The next night as Preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n laye in his bedde &amp; ſlepte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre kynges apperyd to hym. &amp; ſpake to hy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; charged hym y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he ſholde not in noo manere helpe ne ſocour the Neſtorines. for it is goddys wyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ſholde vtterly be diſtroyed for theyr wyckydnes and malyce / And whan the Neſtorines herde tell y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n had ſuche a vyſion of the thre kynges. they yede abowte to the grete lordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were abowte Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n &amp; yaue theim grete yeftes to ſpeke to theyr lorde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they myght haue helpe of hym / And thenne dyuers lordes counſeyled Preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n to take noo he de of dremes nor of ſuche vyſions. but to holde his purpoos &amp; promyſe.&amp; to helpe thiſe Neſtorines / And thenne Preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n aſſented to theyr counſell &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce his eldeſt ſone Dauid wyth a ſtronge ooſt in hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng of the Neſtorines / And whan thyſe two hoſtes mette togyder the Tartarines had the vyctory. and ſlewe Dauid &amp; all his ooſt.ſoo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there aſcaped none alyue / And alſo they dyſtroyed many londes. cytees &amp; caſtelles that were longynge to Preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n / And whan preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n herde therof thenne he was ſory therfore that he dide ayenſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment of the
<pb facs="tcp:10351:41"/>thre kynges that apperyd to hym in his ſlepe / And thenne with grete ſorowe of herte he aſked god mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy &amp; foryeuenes. and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre kynges he prayed of gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce &amp; helpe / Thenne on a tyme the thre kynges appe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to themperour of Tartaryn as he lay in his bed and charged hym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſholde doo nomore harme to Preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n / And badde he ſhold ſende to hym and make a fynall peas wyth hym for euermore. but the londes &amp; caſtelles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> themperour had wonne of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n to kepe theym ſtyll to hymſelf. for by cauſe Preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n was inobedyent to our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundment / Thenne themperour anone though he were a Pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nym. yet he was ſore adradde of his viſyon / Anone he ſente meſſagers to Preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n &amp; made a fynall peas betwene theym for euer more In ſomoche that the eldeſt ſone of thyſe two lordes ſholde wedde the tothers doughter euer more after to the worldes ende &amp; ſoo it is yet contynued unto this daye / ¶ So after<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde this emperour enqueryd of the thre kinges &amp; of theyr lyues &amp; dedes / Thenne in mynde &amp; in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe of theym themperour ordeyned that his fyrſt ſone &amp; al the chyldren of his ſucceſſours ſholde beere the names of thyſe thre kynges for euermore after / And thus the Neſtorines were dyſtroyed &amp; put oute of theyr londes &amp; kyngdoms / And after warde were fugytyf and dwellynge abowte in dyuers countrees alwaye vnder trybute. as Iewes &amp; other nacyons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ben alway dwellynge vnder trybute / But yet ſome
<pb facs="tcp:10351:42"/>of theym dwelle in thyle of Egriſwyll.&amp; paye ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery yere grete trybute / </p>
            <p>Alſo there is a nother ſecte that is callyd Indy. and they ben of Preter Ioh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ns londe.&amp; they ben good criſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten men / Add the preeſtis of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> londe whan they goo to maſſe they hange a crowne of golde on the awter And the preeſt. deaken &amp; ſubdeaken mete togider in thre partyes.&amp; ſoo they goo to the awter / And thys they doo in tokenynge of the thre kinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mette ſo denly togider in an hye waye. whiche was departed in thre wayes / &amp; ſo thrugh ledynge of the ſterre they yede vnto Bedleem &amp; offred yeftes to god almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the twelfthe daye after his byrthe / </p>
            <p>There is alſo a nother ſecte whiche is called Grecij &amp; there preeſtes haue wyues / And they byleue on the fader &amp; on the ſone. but not in the holy ghoſt / &amp; alſo they byleue &amp; ſaye there is no purgatory / And whan they ſynge maſſe they kytte a pece of breede. &amp; that is made four ſquare / And this breede they putte in a diſſh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of golde or of ſyluer.&amp; aboue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they lay a ſterre &amp; that is couered w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a fayr whyte clothe / And at the Offetory of the maſſe they take the diſſh<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth thoſt &amp; with the ſterre &amp; ſette it aboue on their heedes.&amp; ſo wyth ſencers and candelles they goo abowte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che wyth grete worſhyppe &amp; reuerence. and ſoo ayen to the awter / And thenne all the people fallen dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grounde &amp; doon grete worſhip to the ſacrefy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe / And thus they doo in tokenyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thre kynges
<pb facs="tcp:10351:42"/>that ſought god almyghty in Bedleem. and offryd to him ryche yeftes.&amp; thrugh ledyng of a ſtere came to the maynger there Cryſt laye / And there they fell downe &amp; worſhyped hym / </p>
            <p>Alſo there is another manere of ſecte. whiche is cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led Simiani / &amp; they ben men of Yndore. for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> londe aboute <abbr>Ihrlm</abbr>. whiche of olde tyme was called Pude is now callyd Symis / But thiſe men haue but lityl of hereſye amonge theym / &amp; they doo grete worſhyp to ſaynt Barbara.&amp; watche all her nyghte. as men doo in this countree on Mydſomer nighte / And ſoo thenne euery frende gooth to other and bereth abou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te-dyuers ſeedes whyche ſhall be ſowen in gardynes ¶ And thiſe men whan they ſhall ſwere afore Iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices for ony cauſe. thenne they ſwere by the goſpell. and by the thre kynges / And that they done in toke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the thre kynges that ſought god in the lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of Iewes / </p>
            <p>There is alſo a nother ſecte whiche is called Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice. and they dwelle in dyuers londes aboute / And theyr preeſtes &amp; theyr Deakens and theyr Subdea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens haue wyues / And they ſaye noo maſſe in all the yere but at the feeſt of Cryſtmas &amp; Eſter / And they ſaye maſſe of ſaynt Thomas the appoſtle &amp; of the thre kynges / And this they vſe yet vnto this daye / Alſo there is a nother ſecte whiche is called Yſimij / And whan the preeſtes goo to maſſe. they blyſſe the people. and prayed god rule theym &amp; lede theym. as
<pb facs="tcp:10351:43"/>he ledde the thre kynges by a ſterre in to Bedleem to doo hym worſhyppe / </p>
            <p>Alſo there is another ſecte that is called Maronij / And thiſe men whan they begyn ony thynge. then<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e they ſaye in the name of god &amp; the thre kynges / </p>
            <p>Alſo there is a nother ſecte that is called Nicholaite And thoſe men vſe to gyue euery daye thre manere of almeſſe in the worſhyppe of god &amp; the thre kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to poore men there abowte / </p>
            <p>A nother there is. and they ben called Mandopoles And they holde noo ſpecyall fayth. they are in here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye. ne they haue noo preeſtes amonge theym / And ones in the yere they gone togyder in proceſſion to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyrche faſtynge / And that ſhall be on a Sonday.&amp; there they woll here maſſe in the worſhyp of god &amp; the thre kynges / And all thoſe dyuerſe ſectes &amp; other cryſten men haue many other ſpecyall deuocyons to thyſe thre worſhipfull kynges. whiche were longe to telle / And in all the countrees of Ynde &amp; in the Eeſt and in al the londes and kyngdoms there thyſe thre kynges were lordes all manere of people haue thyle thre kynges in reuerence moche more than men ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue in this countre / ¶ And our lord Iheſu Cryſt ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth many myracles abowte in dyuers places in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eeſt thrugh the merytes &amp; prayers of thiſe worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full kinges. whiche thre kynges now regne in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall blyſſe in heuen / To whiche blyſſe by the mery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; Interceſſions of thoſe thre bleſſyd kynges. he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:10351:43"/>ſytteth aboue all ſayntes brynge vs all / AMEN</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>And thus we make an ende of this mooſt excellenct treatyſe of thoſe thre gloryous kynges. whoos corps reſte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cyce of Coleyne / Enprynted at Weſtmeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by Wynkyn the Worde / </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
